<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/">
<Story><h1>Special Thanks</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">Strasa Acimovic</p>
<h1>Contributors</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">Tresi Arvizo, Jeremy Friesen, Alessandro "Adam" Gianni, Lee Reilly, Nathan Black, Adam Blinkinsop, Matt Jett, Evan Silberman</p>
<h1>Guild Members</h1>
<h1>Bonded to the Book</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">These brave souls have a Bond with Dungeon World, and Dungeon World has a Bond with them:</p>
<p>Brian slayed the sleeping sloth. Dylan plays with some seriously scary lizard men. Josh was there in the Dawn Times. None Andy always plays a bloody wizard. Duane has slighted me with his Terrible Idea - Dave on honey-dew has fed, And drunk the milk of Paradise Sam is the Seeker of Knowledge Rodrigo is the teller of tales. Marc has kept the Old Ways secret all his years. (Or something... edit at will!)   Rob holds the keys to the locks. (x) will choose poorly and be killed, unless I intervene. Joe's campaign fronts read like the script from a telenovela. Sage opened his brain to the Worm God first. Mmm, dirt. Mo is the holder of the flame Vivian stole the Knight's heart Rocha published Dungeon World in Brazil! Veng has gained mastery of the ancient secrets The pale cur sleeps on the book, either growling or snoring. NinjaDebugger liberated this book from the Library of the Ages. Ernesto made the Barbarian happen Jay is the wielder of the magical boot of horse theft. Hans holds the key to weaving spells of Uncertainty Adam is the bearer of the Book of Secrets. Zhang Fei has a history of causing strife among his subordinates. I would do best to keep my distance from him. Rick forgot the most important lesson. Curt finds all the monsters that burst out of the ground Basteen covered the ancient tome in fish. Ios heard the call of the Wild Hunt, and never returned. Bill kept the dragons well away from the dungeons. Michael will sacrifice everything and everyone to achieve his goal. Zed of Sosaria stepped through the gate eager to explore. Mike faced the dragon-bears.  Ryan is He Who Stalks Beyond the Walls. I still don't understand the purpose of this. "Who was your childhood love/crush?" Jeremy's mind spent lifetimes wandering the spirit realms, in a deep lotus-trance. Jeremy slew a red dragon, costing him a limb. brian has seen the fnords. Rob kicked down the door in the name of the King. Rick bears an ominous mark in the superstitions of my people. Sayler is a hoopy frood. He deserves a new character class: Spelljammer Buccaneer! Sophie uses this tome to bend realities James explored all of the wizardly tangents. Kem teaches that the only true weapon is the mind. Vidal is the Paladin of the Great North Grimwald is trying to unlock the secrets of the scroll of winds Jason rides the Glyphon Oliver turned out to be good-natured, generous and likeable; in three days no one could stand him. n/a Dithmer is the guardian of the forbidden tome Brandan unearthed forgotten mysteries. Tulip knows where the Bees are. Greenie spoke the Unutterable Name, dooming us all. Neal found the darkness within. Fred has uncovered the true nature of reality Justin hid something beautiful in a terrible, deep dungeon Nathan is the inheritor of a great and mysterious power. This is the center of Thunderweather Leslie grinds on towards the coming dawn. Lucias got tangeled in wizard sleeves. Douglas Justice is King of the Dwarves. Logan lost the phylactery. Nick is the guardian of the forbidden knowledge Adam rode the world worm Rishi "mistakenly" ate an owlbear pellet Jess opened a Doorway not fit for mortal souls. Typhur stood fast, despite the cost Lucien is the light that binds and demands. Joshua enscribed the mark of the ereboi huntsman. To Keep The Peace, Prepare For War Don't need this Silj is completely fucking insane! Jake has a jinx on him. Adam Rajski keeps the wisdom of the ages safe. João is the master of the large sack Francis vainquished the darkness with but a smile. Rob Justice sleeps in the pines. Nicholas consumed the mythical biter brewery's blinding beer. Joshuha forged the perfect weapon. Joe the mythical waffle taunter. The bigger they are, the harder we hit Shawn was jailed for a crime that I committed. Adam constructed the eldritch machine. Matthias took up the nearest tome and thumbed it through Aleria cannot unsee what she has seen. Jürgen Mayer is the shadow that kills you in the night. Gondry mocked my beliefs Pass. Einroy defended the wall. Zed oversaw the accidental awakening of a new god. Hamish is the blood-stained sword of the Black Elf nation Baern holds the bridge that his friends might survive. drnuncheon knifed many people between the ribs Richard, Speaker to the Modrons Wordman wears the silver mask Abrahm wrought the runes of binding I am ________'s long lost sibling. Brought knowledge to the masses. Marielle never learned how to read and has been faking it this whole time. James is the tester of many tablets. Warren wondered what bond words to write Kenny unlock the ancient gate none Martin unearthed the antediluvian arcana Doyce found long-lost secrets in a forgotten library. Chiang-Chen has an ancestral blade-demon in his palm Vincent walks under the scrying sun. George answered the call of the Final Trump. Thom braved the sideways tower. Ryan Webster befriended a young dragon. Conrad saved my family from poverty Margaret delves tomes for knowledge Robert Bruce told you exactly what you wanted to hear. Shane Knysh is the last royal cartographer of the united southern realms Shane seeks what the ancients knew, but chose to hide Experience points be damned I will not slay another farmer! Brian is searching for his father's lost sword. Clinton will play an important role in the events to come. Carmin is the bearer of the cloak of shadows Fax shifted the walls of the dungeon. Owen attacked the darkness. Nick is the keeper of the ancient tome I care deeply for "person1", but "person2" jealousy keeps us apart. Tleroth stood and held the breach. Tran knows where the shoggoth lies dormant. Dave struggled through the 7 Hells to earn this book Sean is heart-bound to Shawna Lee through the Rite of Stone Wood Philippe Debar was blessed once and then thrice. ___ and I have shared dreams sent to us from subaquatic temples of cyclopean stone. Cade hurled the flask Jason drank from the well of common sense. Plan B is kill it with fire, acceptible at any time. The sacred vision reveals the impending death of your master Rhovanor has a shard of the cup of Eternal Life implanted in his chest. Rainswept's sorrow is here with him. The Rogue learned his trade from the ancient Assassin's Guild. Oliver was menaced by a giant owl. StacyRex possesses the Eternal Bag of Happiness. The Path to Wisdom lies down the Eternal Road Luis crossed oceans of time Kristopher despises most people, but keeps it to himself if he thinks you might by useful.  Savage invective befalls those that have no use. I'm not entirely sure what a bond is but kickstarter is making me fill out all of the fields. Jamie waits in the shadows Brian helped batter down the door to the armory. Hilary is thinking what you are thinking. Lazaar is the master of whispers. Brett Zeiler is extrenely arrogant, but is the best at what he does. Pego was there when "Posta! Pizza! Pacco!" was uttered Jack squandered his only Wish on a good deed. "X killed someone dear to me, and I'm grateful for it" Or, if this doesn't work, surprise me! Clark discovered the lost text (and Amanda corrected it). John must cleanse his gear daily of evil spirits. Carl is the heir of an ominous legacy. Richard found inner harmony Kapsberger Stacey raised the standard of Friendship high upon the battlefield. Dan knows the monkeys will be his undoing. Melody keeps the forbidden secrets. Clifford keeps the Arcane Knowledge. Richard writes with the sacred ink of the ancients. Liri rejected the fulfilling of her deepest wish by the goddess. Julien Pirou is in the secret world behind the GM's screen. Bastinan braved the fires of the Hells. I dunno, some pun about "secular funder mentalist" seems appropriate here.  Give me something that matches your fiction and I'm fine with it; I ordered at this level for the hardcover, the pdf and the suppliments. Manilla has given me enlightenment that I can never repay. Dylan summoned forth that which can not be named. Adam saved the holy feline Ulai stands vigilant at the gate. A recent paradox awakened my nightmares of an anomaly within _'s soul; I must fix it for the sake of my sanity. Antoine mixed the spell components The prophetess Seldanha remains ever watchful of the vizier's machinations. Arvy found a mysterious tome. Steven has opened the secret eye of Angra Mainyu. Dom has travelled under far stars of the future Eric sacrificed an eye to peer into the future Tomar can see to the heart of anything. Damien's blade is not magical though  his skill makes it seem that way. Josh spoke the unspeakable tale Dufresne uncovered the means to open a portal to an unholy dimension. The only boundaries that exist are those of the mind. No Chiv is aeon dead and wields unearthly power XXX stranded me in a house of brigands David knew the doppelgangers secret Keith is the undiscovered scion of the hidden realm. Casey is a disciple of the Red Star. Samuel stood with them at the end. Dylan knows the song to summon the spirit wolf by heart. ___ is a paragon of goodness and wisdom; when in doubt, I defer to their judgement. Not sure what this means? Edomaur is the maker of the wood swords of the green magic. / Elkan casts good ol' Magic Missile. Baf is watched by three sages. Lythias sought the secrets of the Serpents' Labyrinth. Will was initiated into the conspiracy of the Duke's court. Ross was trusted with keeping the ancient tome. Rune is the wielder of the warhammer of grim irritation. Oscar is the Secret Fire. None Just make something up. Tom upheld our ancient honors. Andi awoke the dormant evil Chris discovered the first seal. Due to a magical accident she is your sister-clone Jonathan brandishes the vorpal great axe. ???? Steve has emerged victorious! Tristan invoked the forbidden voice. Thunder is my brother, I ride the winds of destiny! Chamelaeon has discerned the pattern of the stars. Ben uncorked a bottle of port. Mark cooked breakfast at the gates of darkness Roman is the Keeper of the Temple Ruins. Flavio is the bearer of the hat of grumpyness. John sundered the Faithless Gate Bolthan is the keeper of the white  flame. Jack inexplicably can understand the language of Dragons. Owen is the ringmaster of the workers of dark creation. Derek emerged from the ruins carrying an ancient tome of eldritch lore. Thoradin saved the vale from the mighty orc king Johnstone doesn't like anything. Sage and I had a violent falling out. Makr stole a tear from the Eye of the World. Tyson reps Thri-Kreen life. Chris killed the crazed cockatrice No bond for me, thanks Bob keeps the secret of the ancient flame wars The party shivered at the sinister sound. Sean punched a dungeon right in the face Drake broke the first seal Lukas fought at the Gates of Oblivion Sean unrolled the freshly minted scroll Scathaigh is the eternal Herald of the Starshadow Alcionne wears the crystal talisman Gabriel knows the names of all the stars in the sky Petrus is nearly proficient with the double-club Brindy embraced the night as the stars aligned. Dave Insel the Bringer of Ultimate Awesome. The Book has filled my mind with erudition Jim climbed the Infinite Tower Kreg carried the Swagger Stick everywhere he went. Ahmad and I studied under the same mentor. Kevin is entrusted with secret, ancient knowledge. Okerstroker broods in the corner with a watchful eye. J escaped the hook that hungers. Matthew 'Jarikith' Monagon rolled the Polyhedrons of Chaos Xthulu rose from a watery grave. Finnian stole three pages from the book of rituals. "Garry awakened ancient magics" Yrkoon wields the soul-drinking sword Gip has the strength to act. Kurt tumbled through the demon door Casidhe hoards any knowledge she discovers Thorgrim bears the Book of Grudges Aaron still haunts those Crooked Hills. Matt was bemused by Gnomish poetry Robert helped me in a time of need. Keith will explore Dungeon World with any who are willing to Adventure! Luke has quenched the fire of creation JB was buried with the Opal of Xul-Gar Mark bears the brands of the seven holy silences. The secret will undo everything. The Demonlords await the Convergence. Karuk broke the glittering crown Zirk came to chew bubblegum and play games, and he's all out of bubblegum Why don't you surprise me...  :) Savannah possesses a true strength that cannot be overcome Falcros wields the sphere of power. Josh Flint stole pages from the leaves of the world tree. Dean vanquished the Great Evil of T'lorin. Brian founded a city out of chaos. Jingo uses the stone, one last time... Wesley was the guardian of the blind. Tim found his courage in the length of long halls and the depth of blue eyes. Cabuster procured the Papers of Possibility. random() Henry dreamed of places strange David has gained the affections of your betrothed.  They may not realize it, but you know this to be true. Bob defended the realm from the horde onslaught. Nex hides in the shadows. Greg discovered the mystifying elixir. John once forged a celestial breastplate Basilios places the celestial crown upon his head Tresi completed a perilous journey to the smoldering mountains. Marshall married my sister when no one else would. Matthew is the chosen vessel of the Spirit of Wisdom. Cameron tells the old tales around the campfire. Felan wields a stalagmite as an improvised weapon. Kevin is the arcane master of the ambulatory eye. Michael read the starry wisdom between the words Mark immanentized the eschaton. Fel stole the cursed book Corinthi brought low carb snacks. JP Sauers traversed the outer planes. Colin is powered by the apocalypse dragon Derek speaks the Unspeakable Words. Rob united the Bee Kingdoms. Matt discovered a wonderful forest for His family. Warzen has a new cat familiar. No bond from me. none Brad evaded the demon by hiding in the shadows. Phil is the speaker of dreamtruth. Scott delved deep into the Book and came out... changed. Jarod founded the Musty Dragon Inn franchise. Travis really should have known better. Really. Justin Wightbred lead the charge against unnecessary escalation. Gary Hoggatt may be a descendant of Erdrick. With words a piece of Brian's spirit will live on in this tome. Ryan is the Master of the Dungeon. Ryan spoke the word Rusty looked into the Mind of Darkness Shannon opened the book of the forbidden. Sally is a friend of the white cat no Brett is the keeper of Secrets Keith the Keeper of Arcane Lore Rob is lost in a forbidden tome of arcane knowledge. Chris begat many adventuring heroes. Joshua is the ally of the animals of the forest Amy incants the story of the world David paid the price with dark magics. Drew looted his War-Chest for this book. Brian controls the chaos of creation. Chris knows secrets even the vizier is unaware of. Pat presided over the sacred smoke ceremony celebrating peace between the tribes-men of plains . Chris knew the lumber consortium was behind the alien landing cover-up. Cork is a master of elemental magic Meg is the keeper of all my stories. Kyree rules the ruins with fortune and fate. Derek released the demon within Adam unlocked the ancient gate Rob shot the food. Nora feeds the trolls. Cravatosaur is the befouler of the sacred pool. Isen is the defender of the Silverhand. Daniel discovered the freedom of simplicity Isabelle and Emma have shown me the way, now I hope to return the favour. Area 42 is a safe haven for adventurers. Chris consults his library Brent harnessed the power of lightning Gregor Hutton had foreseen it. Alessandro gave me loaded dice! Guard—arrest him! Connor is the cookie whisperer Noam is still residing at the bottom of that pit trap. Stefan is the keeper of knowledge Nikolai is the keeper of the Talisman of the Ranging Pack Leo Lalande opened the astral rift between worlds. Gant and Roland have faced the trials of world, and they have touched Paradise. Kyle owes fealty to the Queen of Winter None René deciphered the riddle of the thousand deaths. Dovre the heir the the mountainking, keeper of the ancient hall. Kate sees barmaids Felix has sealed away the cursed axe. In the darkness I found them Malo delved down and down again, deep into the world Drewid spoke the arcane spell from from the ancient tome. Sean was here! Antti is the keeper of the forgotten lore. Larry the unprintable. Erik reps Thri-Kreen life. Redhan banished an ancient evil. The Crimson Dragon falls to my demon blade. Alexander was once a king; now, naught but an adventurer. The Lord's Secret mistress is Adrian Jeffy poked a toothpick through the membrane. nnone Ray is master of the dungeon and slave to the dice. Zachary learned an ancient song, but fears the day when he will be called upon to sing it. Steve sang throughout the night, . Tara fought the gazebo. Chris is the ruler of Pillow Mountain Ungerford's brain aches with the want of knowing. And I will strike down upon thee with great vengeance and furious anger those who would attempt to poison and destroy my brothers. Stephen is the keeper of the book of secrets! Nick is heir to both warring kingdoms. Tucker is the most worthy of all of Carles' disciples. Kevin is a disciple of His Weirdness: Al Yankovic. Whitney awakened the forgotten gods. Marco is the Keeper of Truth A witch put a spell on Ingo. Ben boondoggles. Tim unearthed the true history. Markku knows where the Arkenstone is located. Christian is the bearer of the eternal light Ragnar taught me how to cook on the road. Glenn explored the lost catacombs The host speaks for the gophers. Will knows the Spectre's secret name. Erik is running low on hearts. "Deimen has some strange significance to my god. Any miracle I beseech in his name comes out reversed." Together, Cazantyl and I escaped from a cult. Quinn unlocked the ancient armory. Bard enjoys smelling ancient tomes. Sean secretly transcribes the hieroglyphs of the RJS Empire. "um... Because I Could." You can make it up...just use this name...Sovern Kestral still walks Insanity's Edge Rausdour hates bats Stella Christina Hall woke up in the middle of each night to learn more from this book Thomas decieved the others. Simba left his mark on the town, leaving it under his protection. Irina was taught to make secret potions by the old woman. Arc keeps safe the sacred sigils. Laura has special luck. Lidrick Barrisbren strung his Lute of Lightning. Russell is the bearer of the sacred twenty sider Steve is sworn in life and death to his son Connor Luke cannot use the force. Alitar is the embodiment of Strength. And what do we say to death?  Not today. Just go with whatever springs to mind - I'm cool with anything. Sam wielded the Flame of Creation Irene will make the last stand. Milo thinks the section you need to read is around page 56. Joseph has awakened what lurks in the deep. Elric wove the web I fear Thulsa's rage, it will one day turn on us... James held no love but for money, and trusted no-one but his blade. Joerg is the guardian and wielder of the first sword Aaron is the Gouger of the monstrous Filibusterer. I don't really have one! Balmung is the master of the Crimson Sword "Chroma owes nothing to Dark Jessop." or, if real names are being used, "Kevin owes nothing to Dark Jessop." Skender dicovered the tarnished Glinn circlet I marveled at the discovery of the World. Sean Dunstan spread word of the wonders of the dungeon to the darkest corners of the world. _________ shot the morning in the back with his Red Wings on. WolfSamurai forever sealed away ancient evils from the world Grandmaster Jarrod asks, "When type of monster is it?" Hawk has the largest pile of fail XP. Chris takes +1 forward in any game run by Adam Koebel Surprise me Josh is bearer of troubling truth. Stew lead the charge against the horned dragon Jeremy is always one book away from a complete set. The road goes ever on and on Matt delivered the chalice to the village elders. C &amp; K Together at the End Mendez stole the Wudang Manual. Again. Alec comprehended the multiple meanings of the Zeugmatic Dialogues. Jeremiah was taken by horrors of the deep. Never to be seen again. The Legions of Gremlins unearthed the deathly tomb. John is the keeper of the sacred kennel None Dan binds the sacred tome. David is burdened by the Holy Word. Slay-Tor used the Hardcover to shatter the spines of lesser books Willow is the conqueror of fallen gods Christian Lindke discovered a magical new world Brian is the inheritor of forbidden lore Rob is the chosen protector of the sacred ale. Alan is the wearer of the trenchcoat of pretension Oliver is the master of a thousand spells Magic brought down the gate Fiddy is the master of many worlds. Jason looted the temple of the Ancient Ones Matt followed the echoes of eternity. Yet again following Wightbred into strange dungeons Raf is the source of cosmic grumpiness. Clyde is the keeper of the spoken word. Joel shattered the Ancients' ignorance. Percy unveiled the secret of the Hoss Daniel uncovered the clockwork of the Cosmos Jerome stitched the bindings of the ancient tome. Dungeon World taught me the power of Awesomancy For Gavin, the Truth is more holy than the Book. Brian is bonded to the bonder of bonds. Duke Monte hung out with the Goblins Herman always gets the flaming sword. Ken is the servant of the Secret Spring. Mabon breathes in the wonder of the night sky Kingston leads old friends into battle with Teuthus, the God who crawls beneath the waves. Rob wields the hand, as he journey's forth with the SOG &amp; SAUF Wesley expressed disinterest in writing this Jeff turned down his right to the crown of the goblin kingdom L.X.D. lives on! Gina cast the spell of eternal marshmallows Ianovos restored the link to the ancestral eight. Dreamstreamer camped the Final Confrontation and put an arrow in the Barbarian's knee. Dave has unmasked the Key Master. David revealed the truth - to everyone but himself. Argent accessed the Aleph. Kirby drank from the Ewer of Memories Vicki is a wannabe (though hopefully not forever) Renaissance woman. :) Stewart saw into the spaces between the spaces. toridas unleashes the power within As wizards we are bound by birth to protect the realm against all evil Connaught strove to preserve the ancient code Tony survived the demi-lich. Ben spoke one of the ten secret words that started the world. Kairam is the immortal sage of the swamps. Brandon raised the veil of darkness Darkfeather unearths the lost treasure of... Micah is the bane of the demon lord, slayer of the spider priest, spiller of the silver blood. ? Tewhill broke the bugbear's will. One book to rule them all and in the darkness bind them. Valtiel is in league with the Fair Folk Chris Dulsky summoned an unspeakable thing. Gilmaldor Half-Eleven is the silent assassin lurking in the shadows. Johann warder of the wyrd. Ghost Bear is haunted by the spirits of those he have defeated Mitchifer is the chosen of the God of Death. Michael dreams of worlds inside everyday objects Malabreiga's sinuous body lies wreathed in purple flame Joseph "UserClone" Le May NEEDS FOOD BADLY!  Jeffrey struggled not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the powers of this dark world and against the spiritual forces of evil in outer realms. Fred was lost to reason when he donned the Evil Hat. Mark awoke the gods Murgh Bpurn does it virtually all the time. Stras is the one that keeps carving faces on all the trees in the Godswood. Markus has seduced the incubus of the seven cauldrons Fox kept the nexus of portal conduits concealed. Mattie promised to teach me the weaknesses of the human mind. Nemo detected slanting passages. Danohead, puddingmancer nonpareil. Philip opened the archives and discovered a World of Dungeons Andy reverse engineered the rules of the Universe. David stole the secret that sealed the stair.</p>
<h1>Kickstarter Backers</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">"Blue Hair Bob" Puckett, "Evil" Avi Zacherman, João Mariano, A. Herbert, A. Nonny Moss, A.J. LoPresti, Aaro Viertiö, Aaron "tildesee" Friesen, Aaron Greenspan, Aaron Hamric, Aaron Malone, Aaron Olson, Aaron Potts, Aaron Rowell, Aaron Tudyk, Accidental Fraser, Ackinty Strappa, Adam "Woulf" Fink, Adam Canning, Adam Chute, Adam Coleman, Adam Dray, Adam Flynn, Adam Fox, Adam Hegemier, Adam J. Piskel, Adam Juden, Adam K, Adam Minnie, Adam Robichuad, Adam Waggenspack, Adam Waite, Adam Wheelock Boisvert, Adam-Ross, AdamD VA, Addy, Adreanna, Adrian Brooks, Adrian Burton, Adrian J George III, Adrian Magaña, Adrian Price, Adrian Sotomayor, Adrienne Mueller, Al Billings, Alan Barclay, Alan Clark, Alan De Smet, Alan Millard, Alan-Michael Havens, Alastair Bishop, Albert Andersen, Alden and Katherine Strock, Alejandro Fernández Ortega, Alex, Alex "Ansob" Norris, Alex Baldwin, Alex Bergquist, Alex C. Trépanier, Alex Davies, Alex Dingle, Alex Fradera, Alex Gwilt-cox, Alex Hakobian, Alex Higdon, Alex Hunter, Alex Nuzzi, Alex Watters, Alexander "Elric" Zorin, Alexander Alabaster Hernandez, Alexander Cumming, Alexander Kell, Alexander Keurvorst, Alexander Lucard, Alexander Siegelin, Alexander Wasberg, Alexandra Hebda, Alexandre Denault, Alfred Rudzki, Alison J. Dodd, Alistair Lamb, Alphonso Butt, Alva Hopkins, Amado Glick, Amy Minucie, Anders Bohlin, Anders Edqvist, Anders Scholl, Andre Kajita, Andre Morton, Andrea Ungaro (Ander), Andrei Mouravski, AndrethSaelind, Andrew, Andrew Asplund, Andrew B. Chason, Andrew Blake, Andrew Byers, Andrew Carbonetto, Andrew Collins, Andrew Croftcheck, Andrew Ducker, Andrew Gatlin, Andrew Gill, Andrew Kenrick, Andrew Knippling, Andrew Linstrom, Andrew Maizels, Andrew Medeiros, Andrew Menear, Andrew Muttersbach, Andrew Saunders, Andrew Schubert, Andrew Watson, Andrew Wooldridge, Andrew and Heleen Durston, André Bogaz e Souza, Andrés Acevedo, Andy 'awmyhr' MyHR, Andy Bates, Andy Blanchard, Andy Deckowitz, Andy Goldman, Andy Hsu, Andy Kitzke, Andy Prime, Andy Smith, Anonymous, Anonymous, Anonymous, Anonymous, Anonymouse, Anthony Hersey, Anthony Martins, Anthony Popowski, Anthony Spulnik, Anton Olsen, Antonio Merùmeni, Antonio Messaggiero, Aníbal J. Delgado, Ara, Aria H.Y. Cheng, Ariele Agostini, Arno Ludo, Arog, Aronhiawakhon, Asher Dale, Ashley Clifton, Ashley Raines, Atlatl Jones, Atomixwah, Aurelia Wyler, Austin Conley, Austin Stanley, Azato, Azhrei Vep, Balazs Oroszlany, Balthus Borazar, Barac Wiley, Barry Baker, Barry C. Cook, Basil Lisk, Batman, Bay Chang, Bay Grabowski, Beau McCarrell, Bechamolle, Ben, Ben Archer, Ben Erdin, Ben Hale, Ben Hartzell, Ben Johnson, Ben Leftwich, Ben Mabbott, Ben Mandall, Ben Murphy, Ben Neilsen, Ben P. Balestra, Ben Vincent, Ben Wakeland, Ben Wlodarczak, Benjamin "Bailywolf" Baugh, Benjamin Bement, Benjamin Herr, Benjamin Hinnum, Benjamin James Meck, Bennett Smith, Bernard Gunkleman, Bert Isla, Bill (Gryffen88) Stilson, Bill Brickman, Bill Charleroy, Bill Kokal, Bill Parrott, Bill Valera, Billy Compton, Björn Söderström, Blake Hutchins, Blkct, Bo Williams, Boaz Bibi, Bob Hanks, Bob Huss, Bob Muir, Bob Poteete, Bobby, Boon Sheridan, Boris Belitsky, Brad, Brad Morris, Brad Osborne, Brad Wilke, Bradford Yurkiw, Brandon "Jabby" Jeffries, Brandon Jordan, Brandon Landry, Brandon Perkins, Brandon Schmelz, Brant Clabaugh, Brawley Avalon, Brendan Adkins, Brendan G Conway, Brendan Hutt, Brendan Lew, Brendan Power, Brennan Haase, Brennan O'Brien, Brennan Taylor, Brennen Reece, Brent Sturdevant, Bret Gillan, Brett Myers, Brian "Arkayanon" Holder, Brian "BP" Paul, Brian "Vomax" Smith, Brian A Liberge, Brian Awis, Brian Cooksey, Brian E. Hollenbeck, Brian Engard, Brian Gerken, Brian Leet, Brian M McCarthy, Brian McCord, Brian Minter, Brian Sniffen, Brian Spicer, Brittany Wong, Brooklyn Indie Games, Bruce Curd, Bryan, Bryan Meadows, Bryan P. Chavez, Bryant Durrell, Bryant Paul Johnson, Bryce Bolliger, C. Edwards, C. W. Marshall, Cactusse, Caleb Osborn, Caleb Van Bloem, Cam Banks, Caoimhe Ora Snow, Carey Williams, Carl, Carl Klutzke, Carl Rigney, Carl Witty, Carolyn and Nick Atkins, Carson Hill, Casey McKenzie, Casey Walton, Cat Peters, Catherine Hardin, Cerity Tradewind, Chad, Chad "T-Rex" Laws, Chad Bowers, Chad J. Bowser, Chad Jemmett, Chad Reiss, Charles, Charles Alvis, Charles Long, Charles Starr, Charlie, Charlie Reece, Cheryl Trooskin-Zoller, Children of the Lost Eden, Chloe Katzburg, Chris A Challacombe, Chris Adams, Chris Bennett, Chris Brooks, Chris Brua, Chris Clary, Chris Clouser, Chris Czerniak, Chris Darden, Chris DeCarolis, Chris Fee, Chris Fowler, Chris Gardiner, Chris Heinzmann, Chris Hopkinson, Chris Kirby, Chris Laine, Chris Lazenbatt, Chris Longhurst, Chris Murray, Chris ONeill, Chris Parker, Chris Pullen, Chris Rogers, Chris S, Chris Shablak, Chris Shields, Chris Slazinski, Chris Sloan, Chris Sniezak, Chris Whetstone, Chris Wiegand, Chris Woods, Chris Yates, Christian Abratte, Christian Griffen, Christian Leichsenring, Christian Leonhard, Christof, Christoph Boeckle, Christoph Weber, Christopher Grau, Christopher Haba, Christopher Haze, Christopher Lee, Christopher MZ Sauro, Christopher Maikisch, Christopher Ogden, Christopher Severs, Christopher Smith, Christopher Smith Adair, Christopher Urinko, Christopher W Mercer, Christopher Weeks, Christopher Welch, Chuck Cooley, Civil Savage, Clint Morris, Cody "Pax" Markle, Colin Booth, Colin Cherry, Colin Freeman, Colin M, Colin Roald, Colin and Ian Pinkerton, Connor Alexander, Cookie Saxton-Ruiz, Corra, Count Kirith Urah Kazar, Craig Hatler, Craig Janssen, Craig McRoberts, Craig Perko, Creature Entertainment, Cree &amp; Richard Boyechko, Creidieki Crouch, Curran Carmichael, Curt Meyer, Curt Steindler, Curt Thompson, Cy Myers, D. Weaver, Dag Sverre Syrdal, Dale Horstman, Dallas McNally, Damien Holder, Damien Laing, Damien Park, Dan Bruguier, Dan Cruickshank, Dan Grabowski, Dan Hall, Dan Luxenberg, Dan Marchant, Dan Maruschak, Dan McSorley, Dan R., Dan Rosenthal - Game Law Partners, Dan Shaurette, Dana B, Daniel Brannick, Daniel Brown, Daniel Corn, Daniel Drew, Daniel G. Dyrda, Daniel H. Levine, Daniel H. Spain, Daniel Hartnett, Daniel Hoffmann, Daniel J T Moore, Daniel J. Owsen, Daniel M. Perez, Daniel McKenna, Daniel Morey, Daniel O'Connell, Daniel P. Shaefer, Daniel Roanoke, Daniel Sacdpraseuth, Daniel Steadman, Daniel Westheide, Daniel, Max &amp; Mason, Daniele Di Rubbo, Daniele Ruggeri, Danny, Darcy, Darcy Burgess, Darin Shepit, DarkMoonINC, Darrel, Darren Brewster, Darren Watts, Darth Butternutz, Daryl Gubler, Dave "The Game" Chalker, Dave Bapst, Dave Campbell, Dave Kester, Dave Rezak, Dave Ruppel, Dave Skogstad, Dave Tarr, Dave Younce, David, David 'Doc Blue' Wendt, David A. K. Lichtenstein, David A. Nixon Jr., David B, David B Silverman, David Bolick, David Ellison, David Gallo, David Gilbert, David Hertz, David Hines, David Kazibut, David Lai, David M., David M. Miles, David Macauley, David Moore, David Morrison, David Murray, David P, David Ross, David Schmitt, David Steiger, David Stoneking, David Thackaberry, David Thiel, David V Zarubin, David Wetterbro, David Z Chen, DeShawn Luu, Dean Gilbert, Dean Langford, Dean McNabb, Declan Feeney, Deirdre Calvaneso, Demian M Walendorff, Denis Azuaje, Dennis Kadera, Denys Mordred, Derek Cardwell, Derek Handley, Derek Lettman, Derick Larson, Detective Clayton, Dev Purkayastha, Devin C, Devon Campbell, Dexter Mcdot, Dick Page, Diogo Nogueira, Dominic Claveau, Don Barnett, Don Gardner, Don Schlaich, Donald Tyo, Doug Blakeslee, Doug Bonar, Doug Daulton, Doug Hagler, Doug Pirko, Doug Smidebush, Dougal Scott, Douglas S. Keester, Dr. Ivo Robotnik, Drew Hart-Shea, Druaightagh, Dryn, Duane Moore, Duncan Burridge, Duncan Pickard, Dustin Gulledge, Ed, Ed Casilio, Ed Kowalczewski, Ed Thater, Eddie Clark, Eddie Goehner, Eddy Webb, Edgar Gillock, Eduardo H Schaeffer, Edward Damon, Edward Hand, Edward McWalters, Einar Wolfsauge, Eldergamer, Eli Barnes, Eli Baskir, Elias Mulhall, Ellen Zemlin, Emanuele Mandola, Emery Shier, Eoin Burke, Eon Fontes-May, Eric Coates, Eric Duncan, Eric Haddock, Eric Heisserer, Eric J. Boyd, Eric Lytle, Eric Paquette, Eric Stevens, Eric Stewart, Erich McNaughton, Erick Slazinski, Erik Schmidt, Erik Tenkar, Erika Aho, Erin M. Conder, Eskimo Ace, Euan, Eusebi Vazquez, Evan Franke, Evan Parker, Evan Silberman, Evan Torner, Everitt Long, Ewen Cluney, Ezio "Aetius" Melega, Ezra Bradford, Fay Onyx, Felix Tristram, Fenway5, Fercthu Albor, Ferïn, Filth Monkey, Fitz (GameKnightReviews.com), Flo Hoheneder, Florian Hübner, For Anna, Foreezbus, Franciolli Araújo, Francis Dickinson, Francisco Castillo Segura, Francois Gnosis, Frank "Peach" Piechorowski, Frank B., Frank Blazkiewicz, Frank Fiol, Frank Jarome, Franklin Kenneth Hyatt, Frans Evaldsson, Franz Daubner, Fredrik Hansson, Fredrik Sivertsson, Fridrik Bjarnason, G. Hartman, G.U.B.A.R. Podcast, GS Lamb, Gabriel Johnson, Gamethyme, Garabaldi Montrosse, Gareth DeWalt, Garou Verroq, Garrett Kelly, Garth Dighton, Garth Elliott, Gary Arkham, Gary Beason, Gary Bradley, Gary Gygax, Gary Kacmarcik, Gaston Phillips, Gaunt, Gauthier Descamps, Gavin Cermak, Geekfromtheperilousrealm.com, Gentan Schulteis, Geo Pine, Geoff Bowers, Geoff Dash, Geoff Mochau, Geoffrey William Kennedy, George Shanahan, Gerald, Gerolf Nikolay, Gerry Saracco, Geza Letso, Giacomo "jackvice" Vicenzi, Gianluis Ramos, Gilbert Podell-Blume, Giulia Barbano, Giuseppe D'Aristotile Jr., Glenn R Buettner, God, Gokce Ozan Toptas, Gornul, Gozuja, Grandy Peace, Grant Chen, Grant Greene, Grant Lindsay, Grat McGrat, Grayson Davis, Greg Basich, Greg Fulford, Gregor Vuga, Gregory Heim, Gregory Parsons, Gregory Simkins, Grey Growl, Grimwade, Grinpis, Guenther Kronenberg, Guillaume "Nocker", Guns_n_Droids, Guy Bowring, Guy MacDonnell, Guy Sodin, H Shurmer, H. M. 'Dain' Lybarger, Hal "Venjack" Neat, Hamish Cameron, Hans Erich Biorklund, Harold Balsac, Henning Wollny, Henri J. Bauer, Henrik Jernstedt, Henrique Rodrigues, Henry, Henry Vogel, Henry White, Henry Wong, Hiroki Shimizu, Hisashi, Hjortkayre, Holger Niederschulte, Hualex, Hugh O'Connor, Hugh Pearse, Hunter W., I prefer to remain anonymous., I. Calderon, Iain McAllister, Iain Milligan, Ian Andersen, Ian Charland, Ian Mothorp, Ian Raymond, Ian Rose, Ian Toltz, Ian Torwick, Ian V. Caldas, Ignacio Rodríguez Chaves, In Memory of Dave Arneson, Ingrid Cheung, Irven "Myrkwell" Keppen, Isaac Ahuvia, Isaac Carr, Isaac Karth, Isaac Williams, Ishai Barnoy, Itchetiky Jutmundus, Ivan Vaghi, J Aaron Farr, J Scag, J. Derrick Kapchinsky, J. Myllyluoma, J. Todd Scott, J.C. Lundberg, J.O. "Volsung" Ferrer, JC Spencer, JMF Conklin, JUDD KARLMAN!, Jack Burnett, Jack Gibbard, Jack Gulick, Jack Hay, Jack Kenyon, Jack Miskelly, Jack Norris, Jack Waitkus, Jackson Allen, Jacob D. Adamo, Jacob M. Moore, Jacob Maas, Jacob Marks, Jacob Sulpice, Jaime, Jaime, Jake Cyriax, Jake E. Fitch, Jake Parks, Jalister, James "Cornelius" Patterson, James A. English, James Brown, James Buckingham, James Campbell, James Chilcott, James Davies, James Dillane, James E. Winfield Jr, James Flinders, James Gabrielsen, James Jandebeur, James Jeffers, James John, James M. Spahn, James Newman, James Oswald, James Ritter, James Roberts, James Stuart, James Tadashi Graham, James Yasha Cunningham, Jamie, Jamie Furtner, Jamison T Thing, Jams Mastodon, Jan Egil "Jedidiah Curzon" Bjune, Jan Schwindowski, Jan-Yves Ruzicka, Jani Waara, Janna, Janne H. Korhonen, Jared Hunt, Jaron Kennel, Jarrah James, Jason, Jason, Jason, Jason "Ludanto" Smith, Jason "Zebulon" Greenwood, Jason &amp; Kassie Hanks, Jason &amp; Kat Romero, Jason Buchanan, Jason Childs, Jason Dettman, Jason Flowers, Jason Grabau, Jason Hilberdink, Jason Kottler, Jason Leinen, Jason Morningstar, Steve Segedy, Jason Pasch, Jason Paul McCartan, Jason Valletta, Jay Shaffstall, Jay Steven Uy Anyong, Jays Mackie, Jean-François Héon, Jeff, Jeff Bowes, Jeff Healy, Jeff Prather, Jeff Raglin, Jeff Troutman, Jeff Vansteenkiste, Jeff Wowkowych, Jeffrey Collyer, Jenni Higginbotham, Jens Alfke, Jered Heeschen, Jeremiah Lee - @Trifecta_Games, Jeremiah McNichols, Jeremy Cerise, Jeremy D. Smith (zaydoc), Jeremy Kostiew, Jeremy Puckett, Jeremy Whalen, Jeremy Zimmerman, Jeremy the Green Slime, Jerome Grunat, Jeromy French, Jeronimo, Jerry "DreadGazebo" LeNeave, Jerry Erica Nyssa Aeris Celes Auric Romana, Jerry L. Meyr Jr., Jerry Sköld, Jesper Veje Walton Simonsen, Jesse Burneko, Jesse Coombs, Jesse Kirkpatrick, Jesse Pudewell, Jessica Hammer, Jesus H. Christ, Jet Cyngler, Jevon, Jim &amp; Vicki Webster - (Ryan's parents), Jim Dagg, Jim DelRosso, Jim McGarva, Jim Pacek, Jim Ryan, Jim South, Jim Sweeney, Jimmy "JR" Ray Tyner 3rd, Joe, Joe Basham, Joe Howe, Joe LaFerlita, Joe Pruitt, Joe Robertson, Joe Stroup, Joe Thater, Joe Thomas, Joel, Joey Rodgers, JoeyR, Johan Eriksson, Johannes, John "Wildunknown" James, John Aegard, John Bogart, John Brown, John C. Schisler, John Carroll, John Coates, John Colagioia, John Conklin, John D. Pankey, John D. Wright, John Daniels, John Earley, John Eddy, John Fiala, John Gares Martin III, John Harris, John Ivor Carlson, John Lammers, John Lantz, John LeBoeuf-Little, John M. Campbell, John Moran, John Perich, John Philip Dennis Ryan, John Powell, John Stavropoulos, John Taber, John Thibodeau, John Wilson, Johnn Four, Johnnie Hafley, Johnny Bremer, Jon, Jon Cole, Jon Leitheusser, Jon Sheppard, Jon Stump, Jon Stutzman, Jon W. Kroeger, Jonas Möckelström, Jonas Richter, Jonas Schiött, Jonatan Kilhamn, Jonathan "Buddha" Davis, Jonathan Bristow, Jonathan Combs, Jonathan Ensor, Jonathan Grimm, Jonathan Grosvenor, Jonathan Ingsley, Jonathan Jordan, Jonathan Knapp, Jonathan Lavallee, Jonathan Lee, Jonathan Slack, Jonathan Sue, Jonathan Tiong, Jonathan Westmoreland, Jordan "xRazoo" Jensen, Jordan Barber, Jordan Bowman, Jordan Raymond, Jorge Prieto, Jose Garcia, Jose LaCario, Joseph Ashley, Joseph Barnsley, Joseph Meyer, Joseph Murray Jr., Joseph Rossi, Josh Chewning, Josh Drobina, Josh Foxford, Josh Gorfain, Josh Lynch, Josh Miller, Josh Street, Joshua, Joshua Barney; "Qwitwa", Joshua Card, Joshua Krutt, Joshua Ramsey, Joshua Unruh, Joshua Wehner, José Luiz "Tzimiscedracul" F. Cardoso, Julianna Backer, June Owatari, Justin Achilli, Justin Barr, Justin Cranford, Justin D. Jacobson, Justin Evans, Justin Hamilton, Justin Lance, Justin Melton, Justin S Nafziger, Justin Smith, Justin Smith, Justin Stoddard, Justin Yeo, Justo R Diaz, K. David Woolley, Kai Yau, Kamnev Mihail, Karl Jahn, Karl Miller, Karlen "Sorcerer of the North" Kendrick, Karoline Dianne Keeney, Kas Anarky, Kastor Lieberung, Kat Land, Kate Kirby, Kayne, Keilyn Lucent, Keith Baker, Keith Blocker, Keith Carnes, Keith M., Keith Preston, Keith Senkowski, Keith Stetson, Kelley Rogers, Ken Arthur, Ken Harward, Ken St. Andre, Kenneth Zeranski, Kevin Denehy, Kevin Galloway, Kevin Heckman, Kevin Lindgren, Kevin Lorson, Kevin M. James, Kevin Martin, Kevin Maynard, Kevin McManus, Kevin Priest, Kevin Smith, Kevin Wallace, Kevin Wilson, Kevin Young, Kien-Peng Lim, Kierya and Mordraeth, Kim Dong-Ryul, Kirby Young, Kirin Robinson, Kjetil Kverndokken, Klaus Weidner, Kobayashi, Konstantinos "Yo! Master" Rentas, Kornel, Kristi Desinise, Kristian Cee, Kurt, Kurt Dietrich, Kwyndig, Kyle Buehler, Kyle Burckhard, Kyle Payne, Kyle Rock, Kyle Simons, Kyle Waldo Torres, Kyre, LB Stouder, Larry Lade, Lars Ericson, Lars Larsen, Lars M. Nielsen, Lauren McMahon, Lavinia Fantini, Lee Engelhardt, Lee Garvin, Lee Sandow, Lee Short, Lee Zickel, Leif Erik Furmyr, Leonard Balsera, Leonardo Facchin, Leroy Van Camp, Linda Larsson, Lior Wehrli, Lisa 'The Mouse', Little Spartan Studios, Lizard, LogicNinja, Lond, High Mage of Virtual Cartography, Lou Hayt, Louis Luangkesorn, Lovelydwarf, Luca Ricci, Lucas Servideo, Lukas Myhan, Lukas Sjöström, Luke "Mournful" Jacobs, Luke Bailey, Luke Walker, M. Bair, M. Sean Molley, M. Stevens Chase, M. W. II, MB, MO Balbarin, Maarten Bukkems, MadRhetoric, Madeline Ferwerda, Mads Egedal Kirchhoff, Mads Marturin, Malcolm Harbrow, Malikor, Manohar Coussa, Manu Marron, Manuel  Quick, Mar '  Iastra  Yn  D '  aan, Marc, Marc 'Szpil' A., Marc Hertogh, Marc Williamson, Marco "Mr. Mac" Andreetto, Marco "Sagojo" Tripepi, Marco Bignami, Marco Brucale, Marco Costantini, Marcos Silva, Marcus Bone, Marcus Burggraf, Marcus DLR, Marijn Cornil, Marijn Hubert, Mariko Shewmake, Mark "Dojo" Brown, Mark Bennett, Mark Best, Mark Couture, Mark Diaz Truman and Marissa Kelly, Magpie Games, Mark Diffenderfer, Mark E Larson, Mark Featherston, Mark Harvey, Mark Levad, Mark Maibroda, Mark Mealman, Mark Morrison, Mark Parker, Mark Shocklee, Mark Solino, Mark Steen, Mark, Mary, Nathan &amp; Hannah Watson, Markus Schoenlau, Martijn Vos, Martin Costa, Lord High Phrenologist, Martin Griffin, Martin J. Teply, Martin Ralya, Mathias Exner, Matias Frosterus, Matt, Matt &amp; Nykki Boersma, Matt Boeck, Matt Canale, Matt Clay, Matt Donaldson, Matt Downer, Matt Herson, Matt Hogan, Matt Jackson, Matt Kimball, Matt Landis, Matt Lewis, Matt Machell, Matt Maranda, Matt Mensch, Matt Osborne, Matt Riley, Matt Sheridan, Matt Spain, Matt Strickling, Matt Weber, Matt Wetherbee, Matt Widmann, Matt Wilson, Matt and Katie Johnston, Matteo Sasso, Matthew "Doc" Michnik, Matthew Ashby, Matthew Blackwell, Matthew Broodie-Stewart, Matthew Butler, Matthew Chan, Matthew D. Gandy, Matthew Diaz, Matthew Edwards, Matthew Gomez, Matthew Graves, Matthew Haulman, Matthew Hughes, Matthew J. Hanson, Matthew Keevil, Matthew Krykew, Matthew L. L. Wheeler, Matthew L. Seidl, Matthew Lind, Matthew Miller, Matthew Nielsen, Matthew Parcell, Matthew Patterson, Matthew Rees, Matthew Rolnick, Matthew Rooks, Matthew Uschelbec, Matthew Ward, Matthew Wilde, Matthias 'darkpact' Nagy, Maurice "gilvanblight" Tousignant, Mauro Ghibaudo, Max "Ego" Hervieux (I was a playtester so my name may already be registered), Max Villet, Max.A, Maynard McGuffin, Md. Muazzam B. Sham Khiruddin, Meera Barry, Mendel Schmiedekamp, Michael, Michael "rekenner" Renneker, Michael 'Minder' Riabov, Michael Atlin, Michael Barker, Michael Bentley, Michael Bowman, Michael Cassimaty, Michael Cule, Michael Curry, Michael D Blanchard, Michael D. Ranalli Jr., Michael De Rosa, Michael Fake, Michael Felgenhaur, Michael Gunderson, Michael Harrel, Michael Harrison, Michael Hertling, Michael Hill, Michael Hughes, Michael John, Michael Kailus, Michael Lewis, Michael Llaneza, Michael Loy, Michael Marquez, Michael Miguel-Sanchez, Michael Mitchell, Michael Nutt, Michael Nutter, Michael R. Underwood, Michael Rees, Michael Richards, Michael Spinks, Michael St. Clair, Michael Stephenson, Michael Swadling, Michael W. Mattei, Michael Wasserman, Michael Zautner, Michael the OnlineDM, Michele "Mick" Toscan, Michelle "ChessyPig" Taylor, Michelle Shepardson, Michelle, Connor and Xander, Miguel Zapico, Mikael Andersson, Mikael Dahl, Mike &amp; Keith MacArthur, Mike Addison, Mike D., Mike Davey, Mike Dingeldein, Mike Edmonds, Mike Fitch, Mike Frazer, Mike G Jones, Mike Haggett, Mike McMullan, Mike Miller, Mike Mudgett, Mike Olson, Mike Ramsey, Mike Reed, Mike Riverso, Mike Sheley, Mike Simpson, Mike Welker, Mikko Kurki-Suonio, Miles Gaborit, Miles Nerini, Milton M. Fernandez, Mircea Ungureanu, Monica Speca, Monster Johnson, Monte, Mopsothoth, Morgan Ellis, Morgan Gilbert, Morgan Hatfield, Morgan Hay, Morgan Westbrook, Moritz, Morry Veer, Mr pLoLock, MrFatso from GBAtemp, Murph, Myles "The Funk Wagon" McMann, Myles Corcoran, Myles McCloskey, N. Orlando Wilson, N/A, Nachiket A. Patkar, Nah, don't worry, Narayan Bajpe, Nat "woodelf" Barmore, Nat Webb, Nate Lawrence, Nate Reed, Nathan Altice, Nathan Black, Nathan Frund, Nathan Kangas, Nathan Malynn, Nathan Olmstead, Nathan Russell, Nathan Trail, Nathaniel W Jordan, Ned, Neil A. Pinkerton, Neil Carr, Neil Goodridge, Neil Gow, Neil Knauth, Nels Anderson, NerdBound Podcast, NextJenn Martin, Nic Webb, Nice Man, Nicholas Graziade, Nicholas Hutchind, Nicholas Peterson, Nicholas Riley, Nick "Mystic5523" Wesselmann, Nick "Necronomitron" Garcia, Nick Bate, Nick Brooke, Nick Buddell, Nick Hrinda, Nick Pilon, Nick Townsend, Nick Warcholak, Nick wingedferret Brown, Nicolas Acton, Nicolas G. Kruk, Nicole Trainor, Nicolás Brian, Nightstorm, Nikolai, No name needed for me. :) Thank you. :), No need, Noah Hinz, Noble Kale, Noel Hoerst, Noggin, None, None, None, Not necessary, Not necessary. Thanks, anyway., Numinous, ObsidianBlk, OddHelge Gravalid, Odin, Oh Seung Han(Wishsong), Ola Jostein Jørgensen, Olaf Kruse, Olav Nygård, Oliver Graf, Oliver Northrup, Oliver Nøglebæk, Oliver von Spreckelsen, Olivier Brunet, Olivier Vigneresse, Omer Golan-Joel, Orastes, Ovid, Ovlovian, Owen Kerr, Owen Meldrim Moore, Oxy Morons, PJ, POUDEROUX Stephane, Pablo Iglesias Montañés, Pablo Palacios, Paolo  "vonpaulus" Castelli, Paolo "Koradji" Carnevali, Parke Hultman, Parker D Hicks, Pat "Silverhand" Andrews, Pat Gamblin, Pat Kemp, Pat Sylves, Patrice Hédé, Patrice Mermoud, Patricio Jones, Patrick "patmax17" Marchiodi, Patrick Clapp, Patrick Dawson, Patrick Lee, Patrick Ley, Patrick Maguire, Patrick O'Brien, Patrick S Malone, Patrick Sullivan, Paul, Paul "DQGM", Paul Blair, Paul Casagrande, Paul Cavanaugh, Paul DeMartino, Paul Edson, Paul Imboden, Paul Jenx, Paul Mansfield, Paul R. Plaisance, Paul Smith, Paul Stefko, Paul Towler, Paul Vogt - The Hopeless Gamer, Paul Watson, Paulo Segundo, Pedro Gómez-Esteban González, Pedro Ziviani, Penny Greening, Perry Waterworth, Pete Falco, Pete Figtree, Pete Griffith, Pete Hurley, Peter *LifescanX' Poulsen, Peter Alvino, Peter Aronson, Peter Bensley, Peter Borah, Peter Goderie, Peter Kristolaitis, Peter Schichl, Peter Usagi, Peter Wessel Zapffe, Phil "DNAphil" Vecchione, Phil Bordelon, Phil Burge, Phil Hobson, Phil Lewis, Phil Wong, Philip Reed, Philippe Niederkorn, Phillip Bailey, Phillip Pierce-Savoie, Pierre-Philippe, Piers, Piotr "Ifryt" Cichy, Preston Coutts, Psyestorm, Pudge Dooley, Péterfy Áron, QED, Quentin "Q" Hudspeth, Quinn Conklin, R. Zemlicka, R.R. Michael Humphreys, RSC, Rachel E.S. Walton, Rachel Luxemburg, Rachelle Shelkey, Rafael Chandler, Rafael Guillen, Rafe Ball, Rafu, Rainer Wagner-Ballner, Ralph Mazza, Randy Mosiondz, Raphael Grandsitzki, Ray Chiang, Reed Zesiger, Remi Treuer, Renato Ramonda, Renee Knipe, Reno MWG Member Andy Barrett-Venn, Rev. Keith Johnson, Reverance Pavane, Ricardo Tavares, Riccardo "Hammer" Nauti, Riccardo Broccoletti, Rich Wheeler, Richard, Richard "Zelrokyz" Moss, Richard Almaraz, Richard Collins, Richard Hirsch, Richard J Rogers, Richard Morton, Richard Quick, Richard Sheppard, Richard T. Balsley, Rick Ferraro, Rick Harrelson, Rick Rambo, Rikard Warvlin, Rob 'Wolfthulhu', Rob Alexander, Rob Brennan, Rob Donoghue, Rob Gruhl, Rob McCarthy, Rob McDiarmid, Rob McNamee, Rob Sanderson (@azaroth42), Rob Tillotson, Robert Adducci, Robert Carnel, Robert De Luna, Robert MacNinch, Robert Mosley, Robert Slaughter, Robert Summerill, Roberto Collingwood, Rod B. Spellman, Roderick Edwards, Roger N. Dominick, Ron Blessing, Ron Merideth, Ross, Ross, Ross Cowman, Ross Hunter, Ross Lemmon, Rowan Rose Lily Hazel Middleton, Roy from the RooSackGamers, Rudy "Chainsaw" Basso, Rudy "Hikorzik" Rousseau, Rufo Sanchez, Rustin, Rusty Larner, Rustyn Sa, Ryan &amp; Beth Perrin, Ryan Aech, Ryan Craig, Ryan D. Chaddick, Ryan Dunleavy, Ryan Lee, Ryan Macklin, Ryan Moore, Ryan Olson, Ryan S., Rémi Douence, S. Miles, S. Scapicchio, SJ Benoist, Sabe Jones, Sagi, Sam "Nightrain" Carter, Sam Anderson, Sam Chupp, Sam Courtney, Sam Sowl, Sam Zeitlin, Samuel Briggson, Samuel Crider, Samuel Kruse, Sara Williamson, Sarah Harper, Sarn Aska, Sascha Lecours, Sawteeth, Scientivore, Scot Drew, Scott "The Angry DM" Rehm, Scott Belchak, Scott Bennett, Scott Boehmer, Scott Cunningham, Scott Dierdorf, Scott Gable, Scott Kemme, Scott Kinsey, Scott Krok, Scott Madin, Scott McGougan, Scott Neilson, Scott R. Dierks, Scott Rogers, Scott Sutherland, Scott Taylor, Scott Underwood, Scott W. Fail, Sean, Sean Campbell, Sean Curtin, Sean Duncan, Sean Howard, Sean Lesley, Sean Louvel, Sean P. Kelley, Sean P. Soderlind, Sean Pollman, Sean Silva-Miramon, Sean Wills, Seanovan, Sebastian Haaf, Sebastian Hickey, Selene Tan, Sergio Rodriguez, Seth &amp; Rachael Blevins, Seth A. Roby, Seth Clayton, Seth Flagg, Seth Johnson, Sethariel, Seán Harnett, Shana Rosenfeld, Shane Donohoe, Shane Kirby, Shane Majewski, Shane Mclean, Shane Williamson, Shannon Appelcline, Shannon Riddle, Shari Corey, Sharkbomb Game Design Services, Shaun Hayworth, Shawn, Shawn Fagin, Shawn Quinn, Shawn Tomkin, Shawn Tyler McCarthy, Shelton Windham (taleswapper), Shinversus, Silvio Herrera Gea, Simon "Trooper94" Silva, Simon Crowe, Simon Gough, Simon Paquette, Simon Sharp, Simon Weinert, Siobhan Morris, Sion Rodriguez y Gibson, Sithilus, Soirgriffe, Sophia Lily Alsbrooks, Spencer, Stacey Chancellor, Stefan, Stefano R. Rebessi, Steffen Vulpius, StephaNeil Wolfalter, Stephan Szabo, Stephane Chopard, Stephen Bretall, Stephen Granade, Stephen Henderson-Grady, Stephen Holowczyk, Stephen Parkin, Stephen Smoak, Stephen Wilcoxon, Sterling, Stern Krueger, Steve Benton, Steve Bergeron, Steve Bode, Steve Dodge, Steve Hickey, Steve Holder, Steve Kenson, Steve Knowlton, Steve Mains, Steve Moore, Steven Barker, Steven D Warble, Steven Damer, Steven Grady, Steven Holst-Diemand, Steven Jarvis, Steven K. Watkins, Steven Martindale, Steven Robert, Steven Scibetta, Steven Vest, StingRay, Stuart Chaplin, Stuart McDermid, Sure :), Sure!, Sven Folkesson, Sven Hannemann, Sven Stryker, Sławomir Wrzesień, T.S. Luikart, T.W.Wombat, TAK, TJBailey, Tablesaw, Tadeusz Cantwell, Tanya Cohan-Diaz, Tapani Tiilikainen, Tas Stacey, Ted Cabeen, Ted Novy, Ted Williams, Tellef, Thail, That One Die That Never Lets You Down, The Campbells, The Daughters of Verona, The Great and Mighty Neb, The High Lord Mhoram, of the Dark Ones, Master of the Black Citadel, Doctrina Magicus, The Infamous P.I.G., The Lord of Lime Sherbert, The Magus!!!11!!, The Nashv​ille Irreg​ulars, The Secret DM, The Sutra of Supreme Excellence, The guys at Fort Nerd, TheCatfish, Theron Teter, Thibault Mesmin d'Estienne, Thomas Foss Christensen, Thomas Ryan, Thomas Ulricht, ThorDiantral, Thorbjørn Steen, Thriondel Half-Elven, Tiago Marinho, Tim "Buzz" Isakson, Tim Ballew, Tim Hutchings, Tim Knight, Tim McCracken, Timothy Sanders, Todd Mitchell, Todd Roy, Todd Zircher, Tolly, Tom Cadorette, Tom Flanagan, Tom Idleman, Tom Ladegard, Tom Lumley, Tom McCarthy, Tom Reynolds, Tomasz Pudło, Tomek Filip, Tony, Tony, Tony Dijkstra, Tony Eng, Tony Indurante, Tony Love, Tony Reyes, Topi Makkonen, Torolf, Trachalio, Tracy Barnett/Sand &amp; Steam Productions, Tracy Hurley, Travis Bryant, Travis Scott, Trent Casey, Trent Yacuk, Trevis Martin, Trey Mercer, Trollhawke, Troy "Wrongtown" Hall, Troy Gilbert, Troy M. Costisick, Tuomas, Turk, Ty Sawyer, Tyler Jones, Tyler Lanser, Uffe Thorsen, Ulysses, Umberto Pignatelli, Unisprink, Vacuumjockey, Vera Vartanian, Vernon Lingley, Veronica Courage Wakefield, Victor Lane, Victor Maslov, Victor Wyatt, Victoria Uney, Viktor Haag, Ville Halonen, Vites, Vlad Del Cid, Vladimir Dzundza, Vladimir Filipović, W. Scott Jones, WJO III, WOoDY, Wade "Belzain" Ussery, Walt Robillard, Warrbo, Warren "Mook" Wilson, Warren Merrifield, Wayne "Lumrunner" Humfleet, Wayne Arthurton, Wayne Lauer, Wei-Hua, Hsieh, Wes Price, Weston Clowney, White Paws, Whitt, Wilhelm Fitzpatrick, Will Ijebor, Will Robot, Will Thibault, Will Vesely, William "CallMeWilliam" Nichols, William Ansell, William Carroll, William Fischer, William Gerke, William K Wood, William Koch, Willis Scilacci, Wing Chan, Wojciech Gębczyk, Wolfberry, Wothbora, Wyatt Camp, Xander Veerhoff, Xavier Aubuchon-Mendoza, Xellos, cleric of coins, Yan Prado, Yes, Yoki Erdtman, You already have my name from the adventurers' guild, but I wonder, would you be able to add my two players, Keith Gilmour and Dave Fountain?, Yragael, Z. Dettwyler, ZSP, Zach Clay, Zach Gourley, Zach Peters, Zachary Hall, Zachary Sylvain, Zachary Williams, Zack Kline, Zack Woodard, Zane Ewers, Zippy Schindler, Zontco Gaming Division, [nothing], a-bomb &amp; g-girl, amel, badsmoothie, blackcoat, blanksuspect, bowmore, braincraft, bsx, casey forsberg, christian theriault, craig guarisco, desert steampunks, diversionArchitect (David C. Amarasinghe), edchuk, el Mīko, elmitxel, evil bibu, gaz moore, hellium, i don' t want my name in the book, i'll stay anonymous, thanks, jim pinto (lower case), joel allan, kasinoki, kelly j v, kensboro, lacura17, maiki, mau, mcsquiggedy, morgue, nikobe, no thanks, none, randy vranesh, robert lambert, runester, sev, stefan tyler, tavernbman, teeter, the memory of Ada Lovelace, txelu, wraith808, xiangh, zero.executioner, östen petersson</p>
</Story></Root>
