<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/">
<Story><h1>Influences</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">If we have seen further it is by standing on the shoulders of giants. Hill giants and stone giants mostly, but some frost giants and even a fire giant one time. That got messy.</p>
<p>By this point it’s probably pretty obvious that Vincent Baker’s Apocalypse World, as well as Gary Gygax and Dave Arneson’s Dungeons and Dragons are the reason we made this game. The Dungeons and Dragons Basic Set, edited by Tom Moldvay, and Advanced Dungeons and Dragons were our references of choice.</p>
<p>Our version of Alignment is closely related to Keys from Shadow of Yesterday by Clinton R. Nixon as seen in John Harper’s Lady Blackbird.</p>
<p>XP on a miss can be seen in a lot of designs—the version seen in Luke Crane’s Burning Wheel was an inspiration, but this particular take on it comes by way of John Harper and Paul Riddle’s The Regiment.</p>
<p>Bonds are a perversion of Hx from Apocalypse World with a little bit of the memories from Freemarket (by Luke Crane and Jared Sorensen) thrown in for spice.</p>
<p>Dungeon World wouldn’t exist without cross-pollination from many other projects powered by the Apocalypse. Sagas of the Icelanders by Gregor Vuga, The Regiment by Paul Riddle and John Harper, Monsterhearts by Joe Mcdaldno, and several unpublished games by Jonathan Walton all were part of our process.</p>
<p>The original idea to mash Apocalypse World and D&amp;D together belongs to our good friend Tony Dowler. He was gracious enough to let us build on his concept and carry it through to the shape you see today.</p>
<h1>Tools</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">Dungeon World was created in InDesign. The main fonts used are Adobe Minion Pro, Newcomen, and Archemy.</p>
<p>The original text was written entirely in XML to be imported into the book layout, the character sheet layout, and various other formats. Working in plaintext allowed us to map to all kinds of different layouts as well as versioning the files using Git and Github.</p>
<p>We developed Dungeon World a bit like you develop software, so the Github bug tracker and Dropbox were key tools in making the game a reality.</p>
<h1>Special Thanks</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">Strasa Acimovic, Marshall Miller, Jason Morningstar, Hamish Cameron, Kevin Weiser &amp; the Walking Eye, Steve Segedy, John Harper, Tony Dowler, Vincent Baker, Gary and Dave (of course)</p>
<h1>Contributors</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">Tresi Arvizo, Jeremy Friesen, Alessandro “Adam” Gianni, Lee Reilly, Nathan Black, Adam Blinkinsop, Matt Jett, Michael Kailus, Evan Silberman</p>
<h1>Guild Members</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent"></p>
<h1>Bonded to the Book</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="NoIndent">These brave souls have a Bond with Dungeon World, and Dungeon World has a Bond with them:</p>
<p aid:pstyle="BackerList">Shane Williamson knew no companions. Scott Belchak bears the thanks of the creators. Sam is the Seeker of Knowledge. Rodrigo is the teller of tales. Someone will choose poorly and be killed, unless I intervene. Joe’s campaign fronts read like the script from a telenovela. Mo is the holder of the flame. Silj is completely insane! Joe the mythical waffle taunter. Einroy defended the wall. Drnuncheon knifed many people between the ribs. Thom braved the sideways tower. Shane seeks what the ancients knew, but chose to hide. Nicholas’ “plan B” is kill it with fire, acceptible at any time. Peter knows that The Path to Wisdom lies down the Eternal Road. Kristopher despises most people, but keeps it to himself if he thinks you might by useful. Savage invective befalls those that have no use. Eric sacrificed an eye to peer into the future. Tristan invoked the forbidden voice. Drake broke the first seal. Jim climbed the Infinite Tower. George Shanahan had no bond. Finnian stole three pages from the book of rituals. Gip has the strength to act. Keith will explore Dungeon World with any who are willing to Adventure! Mark bears the brands of the seven holy silences. Keith drew on the forbidden power that dwells below. Henry dreamed of places strange. Josh was there in the Dawn Times. Dave on honey-dew has fed, And drunk the milk of Paradise. Rick forgot the most important lesson. Jeremy slew a red dragon, costing him a limb. Rob kicked down the door in the name of the King. Kem teaches that the only true weapon is the mind. Vidal is the Paladin of the Great North. Adam rode the world worm. Brian is searching for his father’s lost sword. Fax shifted the walls of the dungeon. Carl is the heir of an ominous legacy. Richard writes with the sacred ink of the ancients. Keith is the undiscovered scion of the hidden realm. Jonathan brandishes the vorpal great axe. Roman is the Keeper of the Temple Ruins. Owen is the ringmaster of the workers of dark creation. The party shivered at the sinister sound. Ryan is He Who Stalks Beyond the Walls. Adam Rajski keeps the wisdom of the ages safe. Due to a magical accident she is your sister-clone. Kurt tumbled through the demon door. NinjaDebugger liberated this book from the Library of the Ages. Brandan unearthed forgotten mysteries. Lucias got tangeled in wizard sleeves. Melody keeps the forbidden secrets. Clifford keeps the Arcane Knowledge. Nex hides in the shadows. Duane has slighted me with his Terrible Idea. Marc has kept the Old Ways secret all his years. Rob holds the keys to the locks. Jay is the wielder of the magical boot of horse theft. brian has seen the fnords. Greenie spoke the Unutterable Name, dooming us all. Douglas Justice is King of the Dwarves. Logan lost the phylactery. Oscart knows, To Keep The Peace, Prepare For War. Francis vainquished the darkness with but a smile. Joshuha forged the perfect weapon. Wordman wears the silver mask. Martin unearthed the antediluvian arcana. Vincent walks under the scrying sun. George answered the call of the Final Trump. Shane Knysh is the last royal cartographer of the united southern realms. Jason drank from the well of common sense. Rainswept’s sorrow is here with him. Clark discovered the lost text (and Amanda corrected it). John must cleanse his gear daily of evil spirits. Dan knows the monkeys will be his undoing. Bastinan braved the fires of the Hells. Manilla has given me enlightenment that I can never repay. Arvy found a mysterious tome. Steven has opened the secret eye of Angra Mainyu. Damien’s blade is not magical though  his skill makes it seem that way. Chiv is aeon dead and wields unearthly power. Casey is a disciple of the Red Star. Brian is too trusting. Tom upheld our ancient honors. Steve has emerged victorious! Chamelaeon has discerned the pattern of the stars. John sundered the Faithless Gate. Sage and I had a violent falling out. Bob keeps the secret of the ancient flame wars. Lukas fought at the Gates of Oblivion. Dave Insel the Bringer of Ultimate Awesome. The Book has filled my mind with erudition. Kreg carried the Swagger Stick everywhere he went. Kevin is entrusted with secret, ancient knowledge. Garry awakened ancient magics. Zirk came to chew bubblegum and play games, and he’s all out of bubblegum. Falcros wields the sphere of power. Brian founded a city out of chaos. Jingo uses the stone, one last time. Cabuster procured the Papers of Possibility. John once forged a celestial breastplate. Sean is heart-bound to Shawna Lee through the Rite of Stone Wood. Hilary is thinking what you are thinking. Stacey raised the standard of Friendship high upon the battlefield. Savannah possesses a true strength that cannot be overcome. Marielle never learned how to read and has been faking it this whole time. StacyRex possesses the Eternal Bag of Happiness. A recent paradox awakened my nightmares of an anomaly within Jason’s soul; I must fix it for the sake of my sanity. Dylan plays with some seriously scary lizard men. Sage opened his brain to the Worm God first, mmm, dirt. Veng has gained mastery of the ancient secrets. The pale cur sleeps on the book, either growling or snoring. Hans holds the key to weaving spells of Uncertainty. Michael will sacrifice everything and everyone to achieve his goal. Zed of Sosaria stepped through the gate eager to explore. Jon doesn’t see the point. Sayler is a hoopy frood He deserves a new character class: Spelljammer Buccaneer! Grimwald is trying to unlock the secrets of the scroll of winds. Fred has uncovered the true nature of reality. Rishi “mistakenly” ate an owlbear pellet. Joshua enscribed the mark of the ereboi huntsman. Rob Justice sleeps in the pines. Shawn was jailed for a crime that I committed. Adam constructed the eldritch machine. Matthias took up the nearest tome and thumbed it through. Hamish is the blood-stained sword of the Black Elf nation. I am Dan’s long lost sibling. Doyce found long-lost secrets in a forgotten library. Experience points be damned John will not slay another farmer! Clinton will play an important role in the events to come. Dave struggled through the 7 Hells to earn this book. Cade hurled the flask. Blake has seen the sacred vision that reveals the impending death of your master. Jamie waits in the shadows. Brian helped batter down the door to the armory. Brett Zeiler is extrenely arrogant, but is the best at what he does. Ulai stands vigilant at the gate. Josh spoke the unspeakable tale. Dufresne uncovered the means to open a portal to an unholy dimension. Dylan knows the song to summon the spirit wolf by heart. Godfrey is a paragon of goodness and wisdom; when in doubt, I defer to their judgement. Baf is watched by three sages. Ross was trusted with keeping the ancient tome. Oscar is the Secret Fire. Chris discovered the first seal. Johnstone doesn’t like anything. Makr stole a tear from the Eye of the World. Sean punched a dungeon right in the face. Scathaigh is the eternal Herald of the Starshadow. Petrus is nearly proficient with the double-club. Ahmad and I studied under the same mentor. Okerstroker broods in the corner with a watchful eye. Matthew ’Jarikith’ Monagon rolled the Polyhedrons of Chaos. Xthulu rose from a watery grave. Aaron still haunts those Crooked Hills. Luke has quenched the fire of creation. JB was buried with the Opal of Xul-Gar. Karuk broke the glittering crown. Dean vanquished the Great Evil of T’lorin. Tim found his courage in the length of long halls and the depth of blue eyes. David has gained the affections of your betrothed  They may not realize it, but you know this to be true. Brian slayed the sleeping sloth. Vivian stole the Knight’s heart. Adam is the bearer of the Book of Secrets. Zhang Fei has a history of causing strife among his subordinates I would do best to keep my distance from him. Curt finds all the monsters that burst out of the ground. Ios heard the call of the Wild Hunt, and never returned. Jeremy’s mind spent lifetimes wandering the spirit realms, in a deep lotus-trance. Neal found the darkness within. Justin hid something beautiful in a terrible, deep dungeon. Nathan is the inheritor of a great and mysterious power. Jess opened a Doorway not fit for mortal souls. Typhur stood fast, despite the cost. Lucien is the light that binds and demands. Nicholas consumed the mythical biter brewery’s blinding beer. Zed journeyed to the frigid north to meet Jex. Baern holds the bridge that his friends might survive. Brought knowledge to the masses. Ryan Webster is the prince who married his princess. Robert Bruce told you exactly what you wanted to hear. Carmin is the bearer of the cloak of shadows. Owen attacked the darkness. Nick is the keeper of the ancient tome. Pego was there when “Posta!Pizza!Pacco! was uttered. Jack squandered his only Wish on a good deed. Dylan summoned forth that which can not be named. The prophetess Seldanha remains ever watchful of the vizier’s machinations. Tomar can see to the heart of anything. The only boundaries that exist are those of the mind. Ben uncorked a bottle of port. Derek emerged from the ruins carrying an ancient tome of eldritch lore. Thoradin saved the vale from the mighty orc king. Tyson reps Thri-Kreen life. Chris killed the crazed cockatrice. Sean unrolled the freshly minted scroll. Alcionne wears the crystal talisman. Gabriel knows the names of all the stars in the sky. Robert helped me in a time of need. William knows the secret that will undo everything. Wesley was the guardian of the blind. Greg discovered the mystifying elixir. Rick bears an ominous mark in the superstitions of my people. Abrahm wrought the runes of binding. Dwarven Chris kept dying over and over. Samuel stood with them at the end. Elkan casts good ol’ Magic Missile. J escaped the hook that hungers. Bob defended the realm from the horde onslaught. The Demonlords await the Convergence. Oliver was menaced by a giant owl. Ernesto made the Barbarian happen. The bigger they are, the harder Michele hits. Kevin is the arcane master of the ambulatory eye. Colin is powered by the apocalypse dragon. Derek speaks the Unspeakable Words. Brad evaded the demon by hiding in the shadows. With words a piece of Brian’s spirit will live on in this tome. Ryan is the Master of the Dungeon. Shannon opened the book of the forbidden. David paid the price with dark magics. Meg is the keeper of all my stories. Cravatosaur is the befouler of the sacred pool. Brent harnessed the power of lightning. Erik reps Thri-Kreen life. Alexander was once a king; now, naught but an adventurer. Kevin is a disciple of His Weirdness: Al Yankovic. Ragnar taught me how to cook on the road. Sean secretly transcribes the hieroglyphs of the RJS Empire. Adam saved the holy feline. Drew is bound to no-one. Phil is the speaker of dreamtruth. Kyree rules the ruins with fortune and fate. Gant and Roland have faced the trials of world, and they have touched Paradise. Dustin found them in the darkness. Jeffy poked a toothpick through the membrane. Irina was taught to make secret potions by the old woman. Sam wielded the Flame of Creation. Balmung is the master of the Crimson Sword. Steve wants to know who you truly love. Corinthi brought low carb snacks. Rob shot the food. Area 42 is a safe haven for adventurers. Nick is the guardian of the forbidden knowledge. Leo Lalande opened the astral rift between worlds. Glenn explored the lost catacombs. The host speaks for the gophers. Andy always plays a bloody wizard. Tulip knows where the Bees are. Jake has a jinx on him. Warren wondered what bond words to write. Philippe Debar was blessed once and then thrice. Lazaar is the master of whispers. Antoine mixed the spell components. Rune is the wielder of the warhammer of grim irritation. Thunder is Newt’s brother, he rides the winds of destiny! Mark cooked breakfast at the gates of darkness. Flavio is the bearer of the hat of grumpyness. Brindy embraced the night as the stars aligned. Yrkoon wields the soul-drinking sword. Tresi completed a perilous journey to the smoldering mountains. Marshall married my sister when no one else would. Cameron tells the old tales around the campfire. Jarod founded the Musty Dragon Inn franchise. Keith the Keeper of Arcane Lore. Joshua is the ally of the animals of the forest. Brian controls the chaos of creation. Chris knows secrets even the vizier is unaware of. Pat presided over the sacred smoke ceremony celebrating peace between the tribes-men of plains . Chris knew the lumber consortium was behind the alien landing cover-up. Cork is a master of elemental magic. Isen is the defender of the Silverhand. Daniel discovered the freedom of simplicity. Isabelle and Emma have shown me the way, now I hope to return the favour. Connor is the cookie whisperer. Sean was here! The Lord’s Secret mistress is Adrian. Ben boondoggles. Will knows the Spectre’s secret name. Sovern trusts in the creators. Arc keeps safe the sacred sigils. Milo thinks the section you need to read is around page 56. Sophie uses this tome to bend realities. Margaret delves tomes for knowledge. Andi awoke the dormant evil. Tara fought the gazebo. Richard found inner harmony. Casidhe hoards any knowledge she discovers. Amy incants the story of the world. Kate sees barmaids. Richard, Speaker to the Modrons. Mike faced the dragon-bears. James explored all of the wizardly tangents. João is the master of the large sack. Aleria cannot unsee what she has seen. Gondry mocked my beliefs. Kenny unlock the ancient gate. Tleroth stood and held the breach. Tran knows where the shoggoth lies dormant. Paul and I have shared dreams sent to us from subaquatic temples of cyclopean stone. Rhovanor has a shard of the cup of Eternal Life implanted in his chest. Luis crossed oceans of time. Liri rejected the fulfilling of her deepest wish by the goddess. Julien Pirou is in the secret world behind the GM’s screen. Annti stranded me in a house of brigands. Edomaur is the maker of the wood swords of the green magic. Lythias sought the secrets of the Serpents’ Labyrinth. Thorgrim bears the Book of Grudges. Matthew is the chosen vessel of the Spirit of Wisdom. Michael read the starry wisdom between the words. Mark immanentized the eschaton. JP Sauers traversed the outer planes. Matt discovered a wonderful forest for His family. Scott delved deep into the Book and came out changed. Chris begat many adventuring heroes. Drew looted his War-Chest for this book. Nikolai is the keeper of the Talisman of the Ranging Pack. Kyle owes fealty to the Queen of Winter. Drewid spoke the arcane spell from from the ancient tome. The Crimson Dragon falls to my demon blade. Ray is master of the dungeon and slave to the dice. Zachary learned an ancient song, but fears the day when he will be called upon to sing it. Tim unearthed the true history. Erik is running low on hearts. Together, Cazantyl and I escaped from a cult. Bard enjoys smelling ancient tomes. Kestral still walks Insanity’s Edge. Rausdour hates bats. Simba left his mark on the town, leaving it under his protection. Laura has special luck. Mary knows what we say to Death. Elric wove the web. James held no love but for money, and trusted no-one but his blade. Aaron is the Gouger of the monstrous Filibusterer. Chroma owes nothing to Dark Jessop. Basteen covered the ancient tome in fish. Oliver turned out to be good-natured, generous and likeable; in three days no one could stand him. Dithmer is the guardian of the forbidden tome. Leslie grinds on towards the coming dawn. Jürgen Mayer is the shadow that kills you in the night. James is the tester of many tablets. Chiang-Chen has an ancestral blade-demon in his palm. Conrad saved my family from poverty. John cares deeply for someone, but they are kept apart. The Rogue learned his trade from the ancient Assassin’s Guild. David knew the doppelgangers secret. Bolthan is the keeper of the white  flame. Matt was bemused by Gnomish poetry. Josh Flint stole pages from the leaves of the world tree. Rob united the Bee Kingdoms. Derek released the demon within. Noam is still residing at the bottom of that pit trap. Malo delved down and down again, deep into the world. Ungerford’s brain aches with the want of knowing. Stephen is the keeper of the book of secrets! Nick is heir to both warring kingdoms. Tucker is the most worthy of all of Carles’ disciples. Whitney awakened the forgotten gods. Luke cannot use the force. Alitar is the embodiment of Strength. Joseph has awakened what lurks in the deep. Rocha published Dungeon World in Brazil! Will was initiated into the conspiracy of the Duke’s court. Felan wields a stalagmite as an improvised weapon. Travis really should have known better Really. Nora feeds the trolls. Larry the unprintable. Quinn unlocked the ancient armory. David is cool with whatever we say. Dom has travelled under far stars of the future. Chris is the ruler of Pillow Mountain. Antti is the keeper of the forgotten lore. Deimen has some strange significance to my god Any miracle I beseech in his name comes out reversed. Alec comprehended the multiple meanings of the Zeugmatic Dialogues. David is burdened by the Holy Word. Matt followed the echoes of eternity. Daniel uncovered the clockwork of the Cosmos. Wesley expressed disinterest in writing this. Dreamstreamer camped the Final Confrontation and put an arrow in the Barbarian’s knee. David revealed the truth - to everyone but himself. Stefan is the keeper of knowledge. Dovre the heir the the mountainking, keeper of the ancient hall. Matthew shot morning in the back with his Red Wings on. Brian is the inheritor of forbidden lore. Clyde is the keeper of the spoken word. Kingston leads old friends into battle with Teuthus, the God who crawls beneath the waves. Ianovos restored the link to the ancestral eight. Marco is the Keeper of Truth. Slay-Tor used the Hardcover to shatter the spines of lesser books. Fiddy is the master of many worlds. Aleopheus will strike down upon thee with great vengeance and furious anger those who would attempt to poison and destroy my brothers. Stella Christina Hall woke up in the middle of each night to learn more from this book. WolfSamurai forever sealed away ancient evils from the world. Matt delivered the chalice to the village elders. Dan binds the sacred tome. Fel stole the cursed book. Justin Wightbred lead the charge against unnecessary escalation. Sally is a friend of the white cat. Chris consults his library. Redhan banished an ancient evil. Steve is sworn in life and death to his son Connor. Edouard fears Thulsa’s rage, it will one day turn on us. Voodoo marveled at the discovery of the World. Sean Dunstan spread word of the wonders of the dungeon to the darkest corners of the world. Jeremiah was taken by horrors of the deep Never to be seen again. Christian Lindke discovered a magical new world. Jason looted the temple of the Ancient Ones. Jeff turned down his right to the crown of the goblin kingdom. Dave has unmasked the Key Master. Argent accessed the Aleph. Vicki is a wannabe (though hopefully not forever) Renaissance woman :). Connaught strove to preserve the ancient code. Irene will make the last stand. Warzen has a new cat familiar. Ryan spoke the word. Brett is the keeper of Secrets. Alessandro gave me loaded dice!Guard—arrest him! A witch put a spell on Ingo. Thomas decieved the others. John is the keeper of the sacred kennel. Rob is the chosen protector of the sacred ale. Magic brought down the gate. Jerome stitched the bindings of the ancient tome. LXD lives on! Gina cast the spell of eternal marshmallows. Gregor Hutton had foreseen it. René deciphered the riddle of the thousand deaths. Felix has sealed away the cursed axe. Russell is the bearer of the sacred twenty sider. C &amp; K are together at the End. Mendez stole the Wudang Manual Again. Willow is the conqueror of fallen gods. Mabon breathes in the wonder of the night sky. Kirby drank from the Ewer of Memories. Skender dicovered the tarnished Glinn circlet. Chris takes +1 forward in any game run by Adam Koebel. Joel shattered the Ancients’ ignorance. For Gavin, the Truth is more holy than the Book. Steve sang throughout the night. The Legions of Gremlins unearthed the deathly tomb. Stew lead the charge against the horned dragon. Oliver is the master of a thousand spells. Yet again following Wightbred into strange dungeons. Stewart saw into the spaces between the spaces. As wizards we are bound by birth to protect the realm against all evil. Alan is the wearer of the trenchcoat of pretension. Raf is the source of cosmic grumpiness. Percy unveiled the secret of the Hoss. toridas unleashes the power within. Grandmaster Jarrod asks, “When type of monster is it?”. Brian is bonded to the bonder of bonds. Duke Monte hung out with the Goblins. Gary Hoggatt may be a descendant of Erdrick. Jack inexplicably can understand the language of Dragons. Dungeon World taught Boabdil the power of Awesomancy. Bill kept the dragons well away from the dungeons. Lidrick Barrisbren strung his Lute of Lightning. Basilios places the celestial crown upon his head. Markku knows where the Arkenstone is located. Christian is the bearer of the eternal light. Rob wields the hand, as he journey’s forth with the SOG &amp; SAUF. Joerg is the guardian and wielder of the first sword. Herman always gets the flaming sword. Capellan cares not for your paltry friendship. Rusty looked into the Mind of Darkness. Chris Dulsky summoned an unspeakable thing. Gilmaldor Half-Eleven is the silent assassin lurking in the shadows. Brandon raised the veil of darkness. Simon carried the torch for no man. Rob is lost in a forbidden tome of arcane knowledge. Scott was taken unawares. Darkfeather unearths the lost treasure of. Tewhill broke the bugbear’s will. Michael knows the ancient rhyme. Jeremy is always one book away from a complete set. Mark has sung the halfling song. Tony survived the demi-lich. Ben spoke one of the ten secret words that started the world. Johann warder of the wyrd. Ghost Bear is haunted by the spirits of those he have defeated. Malabreiga’s sinuous body lies wreathed in purple flame. Micah is the bane of the demon lord, slayer of the spider priest, spiller of the silver blood. Mitchifer is the chosen of the God of Death. Jason rides the Glyphon. Kairam is the immortal sage of the swamps. Ken is the servant of the Secret Spring. Valtiel is in league with the Fair Folk. Michael dreams of worlds inside everyday objects. Fred was lost to reason when he donned the Evil Hat. Mark awoke the gods. Jeffrey struggled not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities, against the powers of this dark world and against the spiritual forces of evil in outer realms. Hawk has the largest pile of fail XP. Joseph “UserClone” Le May NEEDS FOOD BADLY! Noofy has adventured all over the world to be re-united with his True Love. Josh is bearer of troubling truth. Andy reverse engineered the rules of the Universe. Mattie promised to teach me the weaknesses of the human mind. Nemo detected slanting passages. Danohead is a puddingmancer nonpareil. David stole the secret that sealed the stair. Philip opened the archives and discovered a World of Dungeons. Fox kept the nexus of portal conduits concealed. Markus has seduced the incubus of the seven cauldrons. Murgh Bpurn does it virtually all the time. Stras is the one that keeps carving faces on all the trees in the Godswood.</p>
<h1>Kickstarter Backers</h1>
<p aid:pstyle="BackerListNoIndent">“Blue Hair Bob” Puckett, “Evil” Avi Zacherman, >B, a-bomb &amp; g-girl, A. Herbert, A. Nonny Moss, A.J. LoPresti, Aaro Viertiö, Aaron “tildesee” Friesen, Aaron Greenspan, Aaron Hamric, Aaron Malone, Aaron Olson, Aaron Potts, Aaron Rowell, Aaron Tudyk, Accidental Fraser, Ackinty Strappa, Adam “Woulf” Fink, Adam Canning, Adam Chute, Adam Coleman, Adam Dray, Adam Flynn, Adam Fox, Adam Hegemier, Adam J. Piskel, Adam Juden, Adam K, Adam Minnie, Adam Robichuad, Adam Waggenspack, Adam Waite, Adam Wheelock Boisvert, Adam-Ross, AdamD VA, Addy, Adreanna, Adrian Brooks, Adrian Burton, Adrian J George III, Adrian Magaña, Adrian Price, Adrian Sotomayor, Adrienne Mueller, Al Billings, Alan Barclay, Alan Clark, Alan De Smet, Alan Millard, Alan-Michael Havens, Alastair Bishop, Albert Andersen, Alden and Katherine Strock, Alejandro Fernández Ortega, Alex, Alex “Ansob” Norris, Alex Baldwin, Alex Bergquist, Alex C. Trépanier, Alex Davies, Alex Dingle, Alex Fradera, Alex Gwilt-cox, Alex Hakobian, Alex Higdon, Alex Hunter, Alex Mosher, Alex Nuzzi, Alex Watters, Alexander “Elric” Zorin, Alexander Alabaster Hernandez, Alexander Cumming, Alexander Kell, Alexander Keurvorst, Alexander Lucard, Alexander Siegelin, Alexander Wasberg, Alexandra Hebda, Alexandre Denault, Alfred Rudzki, Alison J. Dodd, Alistair Lamb, Alphonso Butt, Alva Hopkins, Amado Glick, amel, Amy Minucie, Anders Bohlin, Anders Edqvist, Anders Scholl, Andre Kajita, Andrea Ungaro (Ander), Andrei Mouravski, AndrethSaelind, Andrew, Andrew and Heleen Durston, Andrew Asplund, Andrew B. Chason, Andrew Blake, Andrew Byers, Andrew Carbonetto, Andrew Collins, Andrew Croftcheck, Andrew Ducker, Andrew Gatlin, Andrew Gill, Andrew Kenrick, Andrew Knippling, Andrew Linstrom, Andrew Maizels, Andrew Medeiros, Andrew Menear, Andrew Morton, Andrew Muttersbach, Andrew Saunders, Andrew Schubert, Andrew Watson, Andrew Wooldridge, André Bogaz e Souza, Andrés Acevedo, Andy ’awmyhr’ MyHR, Andy Bates, Andy Blanchard, Andy Deckowitz, Andy Goldman, Andy Hsu, Andy Kitzke, Andy Prime, Andy Smith, Anna, Anonymouse, Anthony Bucchioni, Anthony Hersey, Anthony Martins, Anthony Popowski, Anthony Spulnik, Anton Olsen, Antonio Merùmeni, Antonio Messaggiero, Aníbal J. Delgado, Ara, Aria H.Y. Cheng, Ariele Agostini, Arno Ludo, Arog, Aronhiawakhon, Asher Dale, Ashley Clifton, Ashley Raines, Atlatl Jones, Atomixwah, Aurelia Wyler, Austin Conley, Austin Stanley, Azato, Azhrei Vep, badsmoothie, Balazs Oroszlany, Balthus Borazar, Barac Wiley, Barry Baker, Barry C. Cook, Basil Lisk, Batman, Bay Chang, Bay Grabowski, Beau McCarrell, Bechamolle, Ben Archer, Ben Erdin, Ben Hale, Ben Hartzell, Ben Johnson, Ben Leftwich, Ben Mabbott, Ben Mandall, Ben Murphy, Ben Neilsen, Ben P. Balestra, Ben Vincent, Ben Wakeland, Ben Wlodarczak, Ben Wray, Benjamin “Bailywolf” Baugh, Benjamin Bement, Benjamin Herr, Benjamin Hinnum, Benjamin James Meck, Bennett Smith, Bernard Gunkleman, Bert Isla, Bill (Gryffen88) Stilson, Bill Brickman, Bill Charleroy, Bill Kokal, Bill Parrott, Bill Valera, Billy Compton, Björn Söderström, blackcoat, Blake Hutchins, blanksuspect, Blkct, Bo Williams, Boaz Bibi, Bob Hanks, Bob Huss, Bob Muir, Bob Poteete, Bobby, Boon Sheridan, Boris Belitsky, bowmore, Brad, Brad Morris, Brad Osborne, Brad Wilke, Bradford Yurkiw, braincraft, Brandon “Jabby” Jeffries, Brandon Jordan, Brandon Landry, Brandon Perkins, Brandon Schmelz, Brant Clabaugh, Brawley Avalon, Brendan Adkins, Brendan G Conway, Brendan Hutt, Brendan Lew, Brendan Power, Brennan Haase, Brennan O’Brien, Brennan Taylor, Brennen Reece, Brent Sturdevant, Bret Gillan, Brett Myers, Brian “Arkayanon” Holder, Brian “BP” Paul, Brian “Vomax” Smith, Brian A Liberge, Brian Awis, Brian Cooksey, Brian E. Hollenbeck, Brian Engard, Brian Gerken, Brian Leet, Brian M McCarthy, Brian McCord, Brian Minter, Brian Sniffen, Brian Spicer, Brittany Wong, Brooklyn Indie Games, Bruce Curd, Bryan, Bryan Meadows, Bryan P. Chavez, Bryant Durrell, Bryant Paul Johnson, Bryce Bolliger, bsx, C. Edwards, C. W. Marshall, Cactusse, Caleb Osborn, Caleb Van Bloem, Cam Banks, Caoimhe Ora Snow, Carey Williams, Carl, Carl Klutzke, Carl Rigney, Carl Witty, Carolyn and Nick Atkins, Carson Hill, casey forsberg, Casey McKenzie, Casey Walton, Cat Peters, Catherine Hardin, Cerity Tradewind, Chad, Chad “T-Rex” Laws, Chad Bowers, Chad J. Bowser, Chad Jemmett, Chad Reiss, Charles, Charles Alvis, Charles Long, Charles Starr, Charlie, Charlie Reece, Cheryl Trooskin-Zoller, Children of the Lost Eden, Chloe Katzburg, Chris A Challacombe, Chris Adams, Chris Bennett, Chris Brooks, Chris Brua, Chris Clary, Chris Clouser, Chris Czerniak, Chris Darden, Chris DeCarolis, Chris Fee, Chris Fowler, Chris Gardiner, Chris Heinzmann, Chris Hopkinson, Chris Kirby, Chris Laine, Chris Lazenbatt, Chris Longhurst, Chris Murray, Chris ONeill, Chris Parker, Chris Pullen, Chris Rogers, Chris S, Chris Shablak, Chris Shields, Chris Slazinski, Chris Sloan, Chris Sniezak, Chris Whetstone, Chris Wiegand, Chris Woods, Chris Yates, Christian Abratte, Christian Griffen, Christian Leichsenring, Christian Leonhard, christian theriault, Christof, Christoph Boeckle, Christoph Weber, Christopher Grau, Christopher Haba, Christopher Haze, Christopher Lee, Christopher Maikisch, Christopher MZ Sauro, Christopher Ogden, Christopher Severs, Christopher Smith, Christopher Smith Adair, Christopher Urinko, Christopher W Mercer, Christopher Weeks, Christopher Welch, Chuck Cooley, Civil Savage, Clint Morris, Cody “Pax” Markle, Colin and Ian Pinkerton, Colin Booth, Colin Cherry, Colin Freeman, Colin M, Colin Roald, Connor Alexander, Cookie Saxton-Ruiz, Corra, Count Kirith Urah Kazar, craig guarisco, Craig Hatler, Craig Janssen, Craig McRoberts, Craig Perko, Creature Entertainment, Cree &amp; Richard Boyechko, Creidieki Crouch, Curran Carmichael, Curt Meyer, Curt Steindler, Curt Thompson, Cy Myers, D. Weaver, Dag Sverre Syrdal, Dale Horstman, Dallas McNally, Damien Holder, Damien Laing, Damien Park, Dan Bruguier, Dan Cruickshank, Dan Grabowski, Dan Hall, Dan Luxenberg, Dan Marchant, Dan Maruschak, Dan McSorley, Dan R., Dan Rosenthal - Game Law Partners, Dan Shaurette, Dana B, Daniel Brannick, Daniel Brown, Daniel Corn, Daniel Drew, Daniel G. Dyrda, Daniel H. Levine, Daniel H. Spain, Daniel Hartnett, Daniel Hoffmann, Daniel J T Moore, Daniel J. Owsen, Daniel M. Perez, Daniel McKenna, Daniel Morey, Daniel O’Connell, Daniel P. Shaefer, Daniel Roanoke, Daniel Sacdpraseuth, Daniel Steadman, Daniel Westheide, Daniel, Max &amp; Mason, Daniele Di Rubbo, Daniele Ruggeri, Danny, Darcy, Darcy Burgess, Darin Shepit, DarkMoonINC, Darrel, Darren Brewster, Darren Watts, Darth Butternutz, Daryl Gubler, Dave “The Game” Chalker, Dave Bapst, Dave Campbell, Dave Kester, Dave Rezak, Dave Ruppel, Dave Skogstad, Dave Tarr, Dave Younce, David, David ’Doc Blue’ Wendt, David A. K. Lichtenstein, David A. Nixon Jr., David B, David B Silverman, David Bolick, David Ellison, David Gallo, David Gilbert, David Hertz, David Hines, David Kazibut, David Lai, David M., David M. Miles, David Macauley, David Moore, David Morrison, David Murray, David P, David Ross, David Schmitt, David Steiger, David Stoneking, David Thackaberry, David Thiel, David V Zarubin, David Wetterbro, David Z Chen, Dean Gilbert, Dean Langford, Dean McNabb, Declan Feeney, Deirdre Calvaneso, Demian M Walendorff, Denis Azuaje, Dennis Kadera, Denys Mordred, Derek Cardwell, Derek Handley, Derek Lettman, Derick Larson, desert steampunks, DeShawn Luu, Detective Clayton, Dev Purkayastha, Devin C, Devon Campbell, Dexter Mcdot, Dick Page, Diogo Nogueira, diversionArchitect (David C. Amarasinghe), Dominic Claveau, Don Barnett, Don Gardner, Don Schlaich, Donald Tyo, Doug Blakeslee, Doug Bonar, Doug Daulton, Doug Hagler, Doug Pirko, Doug Smidebush, Dougal Scott, Douglas S. Keester, Dr Ivo Robotnik, Drew Hart-Shea, Druaightagh, Dryn, Duane Moore, Duncan Burridge, Duncan Pickard, Dustin Gulledge, Dylan Green, Ed, Ed Casilio, Ed Kowalczewski, Ed Thater, edchuk, Eddie Clark, Eddie Goehner, Eddy Webb, Edgar Gillock, Eduardo H Schaeffer, Edward Damon, Edward Hand, Edward McWalters, Einar Wolfsauge, el Mīko, Eldergamer, Eli Barnes, Eli Baskir, Elias Mulhall, Ellen Zemlin, elmitxel, Emanuele Mandola, Emery Shier, Eoin Burke, Eon Fontes-May, Eric Coates, Eric Duncan, Eric Haddock, Eric Heisserer, Eric J. Boyd, Eric Lytle, Eric Paquette, Eric Stevens, Eric Stewart, Erich McNaughton, Erick Slazinski, Erik Schmidt, Erik Tenkar, Erika Aho, Erin M. Conder, Eskimo Ace, Euan, Eusebi Vazquez, Evan Franke, Evan Parker, Evan Silberman, Evan Torner, Everitt Long, evil bibu, Ewen Cluney, Ezio “Aetius” Melega, Ezra Bradford, Fay Onyx, Felix Tristram, Fenway5, Fercthu Albor, Ferïn, Filth Monkey, Fitz (GameKnightReviews.com), Flo Hoheneder, Florian Hübner, Foreezbus, Franciolli Araújo, Francis Dickinson, Francisco Castillo Segura, Francois Gnosis, Frank “Peach” Piechorowski, Frank B., Frank Blazkiewicz, Frank Fiol, Frank Jarome, Franklin Kenneth Hyatt, Frans Evaldsson, Franz Daubner, Fredrik Hansson, Fredrik Sivertsson, Fridrik Bjarnason, G. Hartman, G.U.B.A.R. Podcast, Gabriel Johnson, Gamethyme, Garabaldi Montrosse, Gareth DeWalt, Garou Verroq, Garrett Kelly, Garth Dighton, Garth Elliott, Gary Arkham, Gary Beason, Gary Bradley, Gary Kacmarcik, Gaston Phillips, Gaunt, Gauthier Descamps, Gavin Cermak, gaz moore, Geekfromtheperilousrealm.com, Gentan Schulteis, Geo Pine, Geoff Bowers, Geoff Dash, Geoff Mochau, Geoffrey William Kennedy, Gerald, Gerolf Nikolay, Gerry Saracco, Geza Letso, Giacomo “jackvice” Vicenzi, Gianluis Ramos, Gilbert Podell-Blume, Giulia Barbano, Giuseppe D’Aristotile Jr., Glenn R Buettner, God, Gokce Ozan Toptas, Gornul, Gozuja, Grandy Peace, Grant Chen, Grant Greene, Grant Lindsay, Grat McGrat, Grayson Davis, Greg Basich, Greg Fulford, Gregor Vuga, Gregory Heim, Gregory Parsons, Gregory Simkins, Grey Growl, Grimwade, Grinpis, GS Lamb, Guenther Kronenberg, Guillaume “Nocker”, Guns_n_Droids, Guy Bowring, Guy MacDonnell, Guy Sodin, H Shurmer, H. M. ’Dain’ Lybarger, Hal “Venjack” Neat, Hamish Cameron, Hans Erich Biorklund, Harold Balsac, hellium, Henning Wollny, Henri J. Bauer, Henrik Jernstedt, Henrique Rodrigues, Henry, Henry Vogel, Henry White, Henry Wong, Hiroki Shimizu, Hisashi, Hjortkayre, Holger Niederschulte, Hualex, Hugh O’Connor, Hugh Pearse, Hunter W., I. Calderon, Iain McAllister, Iain Milligan, Ian Andersen, Ian Charland, Ian Mothorp, Ian Raymond, Ian Rose, Ian Toltz, Ian Torwick, Ian V. Caldas, Ignacio Rodríguez Chaves, Ingrid Cheung, Irven “Myrkwell” Keppen, Isaac Ahuvia, Isaac Carr, Isaac Karth, Isaac Williams, Ishai Barnoy, Itchetiky Jutmundus, Ivan Vaghi, J Aaron Farr, J Scag, J. Derrick Kapchinsky, J. Myllyluoma, J. Todd Scott, J.C. Lundberg, J.O. “Volsung” Ferrer, Jack Burnett, Jack Gibbard, Jack Gulick, Jack Hay, Jack Kenyon, Jack Miskelly, Jack Norris, Jack Waitkus, Jackson Allen, Jacob D. Adamo, Jacob M. Moore, Jacob Maas, Jacob Marks, Jacob Sulpice, Jaime, Jaime, Jake Cyriax, Jake E. Fitch, Jake Parks, Jalister, James “Cornelius” Patterson, James A. English, James Brown, James Buckingham, James Campbell, James Chilcott, James Davies, James Dillane, James E. Winfield Jr, James Flinders, James Gabrielsen, James Jandebeur, James Jeffers, James John, James M. Spahn, James Newman, James Oswald, James Ritter, James Roberts, James Stuart, James Tadashi Graham, James Yasha Cunningham, Jamie, Jamie Furtner, Jamison T Thing, Jams Mastodon, Jan Egil “Jedidiah Curzon” Bjune, Jan Schwindowski, Jan-Yves Ruzicka, Jani Waara, Janna, Janne H. Korhonen, Jared Hunt, Jaron Kennel, Jarrah James, Jason, Jason, Jason, Jason “Ludanto” Smith, Jason “Zebulon” Greenwood, Jason &amp; Kassie Hanks, Jason &amp; Kat Romero, Jason Buchanan, Jason Childs, Jason Dettman, Jason Flowers, Jason Grabau, Jason Hilberdink, Jason King, Jason Kottler, Jason Leinen, Jason Morningstar &amp; Steve Segedy, Jason Pasch, Jason Paul McCartan, Jason Valletta, Jay Shaffstall, Jay Steven Uy Anyong, Jays Mackie, JC Spencer, Jean-François Héon, Jeff, Jeff Bowes, Jeff Healy, Jeff Prather, Jeff Raglin, Jeff Troutman, Jeff Vansteenkiste, Jeff Wowkowych, Jeffrey Collyer, Jenni Higginbotham, Jens Alfke, Jered Heeschen, Jeremiah Lee - @Trifecta_Games, Jeremiah McNichols, Jeremy Cerise, Jeremy D. Smith (zaydoc), Jeremy Kostiew, Jeremy Puckett, Jeremy the Green Slime, Jeremy Whalen, Jeremy Zimmerman, Jerome Grunat, Jeromy French, Jeronimo, Jerry “DreadGazebo” LeNeave, Jerry Erica Nyssa Aeris Celes Auric Romana, Jerry L. Meyr Jr., Jerry Sköld, Jesper Veje Walton Simonsen, Jesse Burneko, Jesse Coombs, Jesse Kirkpatrick, Jesse Pudewell, Jessica Hammer, Jet Cyngler, Jevon, Jim &amp; Vicki Webster - (Ryan’s parents), Jim Dagg, Jim DelRosso, Jim McGarva, Jim Pacek, jim pinto, Jim Ryan, Jim South, Jim Sweeney, Jimmy “JR” Ray Tyner 3rd, JMF Conklin, Joe, Joe Basham, Joe Howe, Joe LaFerlita, Joe Pruitt, Joe Robertson, Joe Stroup, Joe Thater, Joe Thomas, Joel, joel allan, Joey Rodgers, JoeyR, Johan Eriksson, Johannes, John “Wildunknown” James, John Aegard, John Bogart, John Brown, John C. Schisler, John Carroll, John Coates, John Colagioia, John Conklin, John D. Pankey, John D. Wright, John Daniels, John Earley, John Eddy, John Fiala, John Gares Martin III, John Harris, John Ivor Carlson, John Lammers, John Lantz, John LeBoeuf-Little, John M. Campbell, John Moran, John Perich, John Philip Dennis Ryan, John Powell, John Stavropoulos, John Taber, John Thibodeau, John Ward, John Wilson, Johnn Four, Johnnie Hafley, Johnny Bremer, Jon, Jon Cole, Jon Leitheusser, Jon Sheppard, Jon Stump, Jon Stutzman, Jon Stutzman, Jon W. Kroeger, Jonas Möckelström, Jonas Richter, Jonas Schiött, Jonatan Kilhamn, Jonathan “Buddha” Davis, Jonathan Bristow, Jonathan Combs, Jonathan Ensor, Jonathan Grimm, Jonathan Grosvenor, Jonathan Ingsley, Jonathan Jordan, Jonathan Knapp, Jonathan Lavallee, Jonathan Lee, Jonathan Slack, Jonathan Sue, Jonathan Tiong, Jonathan Westmoreland, Jordan “xRazoo” Jensen, Jordan Barber, Jordan Bowman, Jordan Raymond, Jorge Prieto, Jose Garcia, Jose LaCario, Joseph Ashley, Joseph Barnsley, Joseph Meyer, Joseph Murray Jr., Joseph Rossi, Josh Chewning, Josh Drobina, Josh Foxford, Josh Gorfain, Josh Lynch, Josh Miller, Josh Street, Joshua, Joshua Barney; “Qwitwa”, Joshua Card, Joshua Krutt, Joshua Ramsey, Joshua Unruh, Joshua Wehner, José Luiz “Tzimiscedracul” F. Cardoso, João Mariano, Juan “The Barbarian” Gonzalez, JUDD KARLMAN!, Julianna Backer, June Owatari, Justin Achilli, Justin Barr, Justin Cranford, Justin D. Jacobson, Justin Evans, Justin Hamilton, Justin Lance, Justin Melton, Justin S Nafziger, Justin Smith, Justin Smith, Justin Stoddard, Justin Yeo, Justo R Diaz, K. David Woolley, Kai Yau, Kamnev Mihail, Karl Jahn, Karl Miller, Karlen “Sorcerer of the North” Kendrick, Karoline Dianne Keeney, Kas Anarky, kasinoki, Kastor Lieberung, Kat Land, Kate Kirby, Kayne, Keilyn Lucent, Keith Baker, Keith Blocker, Keith Carnes, Keith Gilmour, Dave Fountain and Doug Hare, Keith M., Keith Preston, Keith Senkowski, Keith Stetson, Kelley Rogers, kelly j v, Ken Arthur, Ken Harward, Ken St. Andre, Kendall Shields, Kenneth Zeranski, kensboro, Kevin Denehy, Kevin Galloway, Kevin Heckman, Kevin Lindgren, Kevin Lorson, Kevin M. James, Kevin Martin, Kevin Maynard, Kevin McManus, Kevin Priest, Kevin Smith, Kevin Wallace, Kevin Wilson, Kevin Young, Kien-Peng Lim, Kierya and Mordraeth, Kim Dong-Ryul, Kirby Young, Kirin Robinson, Kjetil Kverndokken, Klaus Weidner, Kobayashi, Konstantinos “Yo! Master” Rentas, Kornel, Kristi Desinise, Kristian Cee, Kurt, Kurt Dietrich, Kwyndig, Kyle Buehler, Kyle Burckhard, Kyle Payne, Kyle Rock, Kyle Simons, Kyle Waldo Torres, Kyre, lacura17, Larry Lade, Lars Ericson, Lars Larsen, Lars M. Nielsen, Lauren McMahon, Lavinia Fantini, LB Stouder, Lee Engelhardt, Lee Garvin, Lee Sandow, Lee Short, Lee Zickel, Leif Erik Furmyr, Leonard Balsera, Leonardo Facchin, Leroy Van Camp, Linda Larsson, Lior Wehrli, Lisa ’The Mouse’, Little Spartan Studios, Lizard, LogicNinja, Lond, High Mage of Virtual Cartography, Lou Hayt, Louis Luangkesorn, Lovelydwarf, Luca Ricci, Lucas Servideo, Lukas Myhan, Lukas Sjöström, Luke “Mournful” Jacobs, Luke Bailey, Luke Walker, M. Bair, M. Sean Molley, M. Stevens Chase, M. W. II, Maarten Bukkems, Madeline Ferwerda, MadRhetoric, Mads Egedal Kirchhoff, Mads Marturin, maiki, Malcolm Harbrow, Malikor, Manohar Coussa, Manu Marron, Mar ’  Iastra  Yn  D ’  aan, Marc, Marc ’Szpil’ A., Marc Hertogh, Marc Williamson, Marco “Mr. Mac” Andreetto, Marco “Sagojo” Tripepi, Marco Bignami, Marco Brucale, Marco Costantini, Marcos Silva, Marcus Bone, Marcus Burggraf, Marcus DLR, Marijn Cornil, Marijn Hubert, Mariko Shewmake, Mark “Dojo” Brown, Mark Bennett, Mark Best, Mark Couture, Mark Diaz Truman and Marissa Kelly, Magpie Games, Mark Diffenderfer, Mark E Larson, Mark Featherston, Mark Harvey, Mark Levad, Mark Maibroda, Mark Mealman, Mark Morrison, Mark Parker, Mark Shocklee, Mark Solino, Mark Steen, Mark, Mary, Nathan &amp; Hannah Watson, Markus Schoenlau, Martijn Vos, Martin Costa, Lord High Phrenologist, Martin Griffin, Martin J. Teply, Martin Ralya, Mathias Exner, Matias Frosterus, Matt, Matt &amp; Nykki Boersma, Matt and Katie Johnston, Matt Boeck, Matt Canale, Matt Clay, Matt Donaldson, Matt Downer, Matt Herson, Matt Hogan, Matt Jackson, Matt Kimball, Matt Landis, Matt Lewis, Matt Machell, Matt Maranda, Matt Mensch, Matt Osborne, Matt Riley, Matt Sheridan, Matt Spain, Matt Strickling, Matt Weber, Matt Wetherbee, Matt Widmann, Matt Wilson, Matteo Sasso, Matthew “Doc” Michnik, Matthew Ashby, Matthew Blackwell, Matthew Broodie-Stewart, Matthew Butler, Matthew Chan, Matthew D. Gandy, Matthew Diaz, Matthew Edwards, Matthew Gomez, Matthew Graves, Matthew Haulman, Matthew Hughes, Matthew J. Hanson, Matthew Keevil, Matthew Krykew, Matthew L. L. Wheeler, Matthew L. Seidl, Matthew Lind, Matthew Miller, Matthew Nielsen, Matthew Parcell, Matthew Patterson, Matthew Rees, Matthew Rolnick, Matthew Rooks, Matthew Uschelbec, Matthew Ward, Matthew Wilde, Matthias ’darkpact’ Nagy, mau, Maurice “gilvanblight” Tousignant, Mauro Ghibaudo, Max “Ego” Hervieux, Max Villet, Max.A, Maynard McGuffin, MB, mcsquiggedy, Md. Muazzam B. Sham Khiruddin, Meera Barry, Mendel Schmiedekamp, Michael, Michael “rekenner” Renneker, Michael ’Minder’ Riabov, Michael Atlin, Michael Barker, Michael Bentley, Michael Bowman, Michael Cassimaty, Michael Cule, Michael Curry, Michael D Blanchard, Michael D. Ranalli Jr., Michael De Rosa, Michael Fake, Michael Felgenhaur, Michael Gunderson, Michael Harrel, Michael Harrison, Michael Hertling, Michael Hill, Michael Hughes, Michael John, Michael Kailus, Michael Lewis, Michael Llaneza, Michael Loy, Michael Marquez, Michael Miguel-Sanchez, Michael Mitchell, Michael Nutt, Michael Nutter, Michael R. Underwood, Michael Rees, Michael Richards, Michael Spinks, Michael St. Clair, Michael Stephenson, Michael Swadling, Michael the OnlineDM, Michael W. Mattei, Michael Wasserman, Michael Zautner, Michele “Mick” Toscan, Michelle “ChessyPig” Taylor, Michelle Shepardson, Michelle, Connor and Xander, Miguel Zapico, Mikael Andersson, Mikael Dahl, Mike &amp; Keith MacArthur, Mike Addison, Mike D., Mike Davey, Mike Dingeldein, Mike Edmonds, Mike Fitch, Mike Frazer, Mike G Jones, Mike Haggett, Mike McMullan, Mike Miller, Mike Mudgett, Mike Olson, Mike Ramsey, Mike Reed, Mike Riverso, Mike Sheley, Mike Simpson, Mike Welker, Mikko Kurki-Suonio, Miles Gaborit, Miles Nerini, Milton M. Fernandez, Mircea Ungureanu, MO Balbarin, Monica Speca, Monster Johnson, Monte, Mopsothoth, Morgan Ellis, Morgan Gilbert, Morgan Hatfield, Morgan Hay, Morgan Westbrook, morgue, Moritz, Morry Veer, Mr pLoLock, MrFatso from GBAtemp, Murph, Myles “The Funk Wagon” McMann, Myles Corcoran, Myles McCloskey, N. Orlando Wilson, Nachiket A. Patkar, Narayan Bajpe, Nat “woodelf” Barmore, Nat Webb, Nate Lawrence, Nate Reed, Nathan Altice, Nathan Black, Nathan Frund, Nathan Kangas, Nathan Malynn, Nathan Olmstead, Nathan Russell, Nathan Trail, Nathaniel W Jordan, Ned, Neil A. Pinkerton, Neil Carr, Neil Goodridge, Neil Gow, Neil Knauth, Nels Anderson, NerdBound Podcast, NextJenn Martin, Nic Webb, Nice Man, Nicholas Graziade, Nicholas Hutchind, Nicholas Peterson, Nicholas Riley, Nick “Mystic5523” Wesselmann, Nick “Necronomitron” Garcia, Nick Bate, Nick Brooke, Nick Buddell, Nick Hrinda, Nick Pilon, Nick Townsend, Nick Warcholak, Nick wingedferret Brown, Nicolas Acton, Nicolas G. Kruk, Nicole Trainor, Nicolás Brian, Nightstorm, nikobe, Nikolai, Noah Hinz, Noble Kale, Noel Hoerst, Noggin, none, Numinous, ObsidianBlk, OddHelge Gravalid, Odin, Oh Seung Han(Wishsong), Ola Jostein Jørgensen, Olaf Kruse, Olav Nygård, Oliver Graf, Oliver Northrup, Oliver Nøglebæk, Oliver von Spreckelsen, Olivier Brunet, Olivier Vigneresse, Omer Golan-Joel, Orastes, Ovid, Ovlovian, Owen Kerr, Owen Meldrim Moore, Oxy Morons, Pablo Iglesias Montañés, Pablo Palacios, Paolo  “vonpaulus” Castelli, Paolo “Koradji” Carnevali, Parke Hultman, Parker D Hicks, Pat “Silverhand” Andrews, Pat Gamblin, Pat Kemp, Pat Sylves, Patrice Hédé, Patrice Mermoud, Patricio Jones, Patrick “patmax17” Marchiodi, Patrick Clapp, Patrick Dawson, Patrick Lee, Patrick Ley, Patrick Maguire, Patrick O’Brien, Patrick S Malone, Patrick Sullivan, Paul, Paul “DQGM”, Paul Blair, Paul Casagrande, Paul Cavanaugh, Paul DeMartino, Paul Edson, Paul Imboden, Paul Jenx, Paul Mansfield, Paul R. Plaisance, Paul Smith, Paul Stefko, Paul Towler, Paul Vogt - The Hopeless Gamer, Paul Watson, Paulo Segundo, Pedro Gómez-Esteban González, Pedro Ziviani, Penny Greening, Perry Waterworth, Pete Falco, Pete Figtree, Pete Griffith, Pete Hurley, Peter *LifescanX’ Poulsen, Peter Alvino, Peter Aronson, Peter Bensley, Peter Borah, Peter Goderie, Peter Kristolaitis, Peter Schichl, Peter Usagi, Peter Wessel Zapffe, Phil “DNAphil” Vecchione, Phil Bordelon, Phil Burge, Phil Hobson, Phil Lewis, Phil Wong, Philip Reed, Philippe Niederkorn, Phillip Bailey, Phillip Pierce-Savoie, Pierre-Philippe, Piers, Piotr “Ifryt” Cichy, PJ, POUDEROUX Stephane, Preston Coutts, Psyestorm, Pudge Dooley, Péterfy Áron, QED, Quentin “Q” Hudspeth, Quinn Conklin, R. Zemlicka, R.R. Michael Humphreys, Rachel E.S. Walton, Rachel Luxemburg, Rachelle Shelkey, Rafael Chandler, Rafael Guillen, Rafe Ball, Rafu, Rainer Wagner-Ballner, Ralph Mazza, Randy Mosiondz, randy vranesh, Raphael Grandsitzki, Ray Chiang, Reed Zesiger, Remi Treuer, Renato Ramonda, Renee Knipe, Reno MWG Member Andy Barrett-Venn, Rev. Keith Johnson, Reverance Pavane, Ricardo Tavares, Riccardo “Hammer” Nauti, Riccardo Broccoletti, Rich Wheeler, Richard, Richard “Zelrokyz” Moss, Richard Almaraz, Richard Collins, Richard Hirsch, Richard J Rogers, Richard Morton, Richard Quick, Richard Sheppard, Richard T. Balsley, Rick Ferraro, Rick Harrelson, Rick Rambo, Rikard Warvlin, Rob ’Wolfthulhu’, Rob Alexander, Rob Brennan, Rob Donoghue, Rob Gruhl, Rob McCarthy, Rob McDiarmid, Rob McNamee, Rob Sanderson (@azaroth42), Rob Tillotson, Robert Adducci, Robert Carnel, Robert De Luna, robert lambert, Robert MacNinch, Robert Mosley, Robert Slaughter, Robert Summerill, Roberto Collingwood, Rod B. Spellman, Roderick Edwards, Roger N. Dominick, Ron Blessing, Ron Merideth, Ross, Ross, Ross Cowman, Ross Hunter, Ross Lemmon, Rowan Rose Lily Hazel Middleton, Roy from the RooSackGamers, RSC, Rudy “Chainsaw” Basso, Rudy “Hikorzik” Rousseau, Rufo Sanchez, runester, Rustin, Rusty Larner, Rustyn Sa, Ryan &amp; Beth Perrin, Ryan Aech, Ryan Craig, Ryan D. Chaddick, Ryan Dunleavy, Ryan Lee, Ryan Macklin, Ryan Moore, Ryan Olson, Ryan S., Rémi Douence, S. Miles, S. Scapicchio, Sabe Jones, Sagi, Sam “Nightrain” Carter, Sam Anderson, Sam Chupp, Sam Courtney, Sam Sowl, Sam Zeitlin, Samuel Briggson, Samuel Crider, Samuel Kruse, Sara Williamson, Sarah Harper, Sarn Aska, Sascha Lecours, Sawteeth, ScantronTB, Scientivore, Scot Drew, Scott “The Angry DM” Rehm, Scott Belchak, Scott Bennett, Scott Boehmer, Scott Cunningham, Scott Dierdorf, Scott Gable, Scott Kemme, Scott Kinsey, Scott Krok, Scott Madin, Scott McGougan, Scott Neilson, Scott R. Dierks, Scott Rogers, Scott Sutherland, Scott Taylor, Scott Underwood, Scott W. Fail, Sean, Sean Campbell, Sean Curtin, Sean Duncan, Sean Howard, Sean Lesley, Sean Louvel, Sean P. Kelley, Sean P. Soderlind, Sean Pollman, Sean Silva-Miramon, Sean Wills, Seanovan, Sebastian Haaf, Sebastian Hickey, Selene Tan, Sergio Rodriguez, Seth &amp; Rachael Blevins, Seth A. Roby, Seth Clayton, Seth Flagg, Seth Johnson, Sethariel, sev, Seán Harnett, Shana Rosenfeld, Shane Donohoe, Shane Kirby, Shane Majewski, Shane Mclean, Shannon Appelcline, Shannon Riddle, Shari Corey, Sharkbomb Game Design Services, Shaun Hayworth, Shawn, Shawn Fagin, Shawn Quinn, Shawn Tomkin, Shawn Tyler McCarthy, Shelton Windham (taleswapper), Shinversus, Silvio Herrera Gea, Simon “Trooper94” Silva, Simon Crowe, Simon Gough, Simon Paquette, Simon Sharp, Simon Weinert, Siobhan Morris, Sion Rodriguez y Gibson, Sithilus, SJ Benoist, Soirgriffe, Sophia Lily Alsbrooks, Spencer, Stacey Chancellor, Stefan, stefan tyler, Stefano R. Rebessi, Steffen Vulpius, Stephan Szabo, Stephane Chopard, StephaNeil Wolfalter, Stephen Bretall, Stephen Granade, Stephen Henderson-Grady, Stephen Holowczyk, Stephen Parkin, Stephen Smoak, Stephen Wilcoxon, Sterling, Stern Krueger, Steve Benton, Steve Bergeron, Steve Bode, Steve Dodge, Steve Hickey, Steve Holder, Steve Kenson, Steve Knowlton, Steve Mains, Steve Moore, Steven Barker, Steven D Warble, Steven Damer, Steven Grady, Steven Holst-Diemand, Steven Jarvis, Steven K. Watkins, Steven Martindale, Steven Robert, Steven Scibetta, Steven Vest, StingRay, Stuart Chaplin, Stuart McDermid, Sven Folkesson, Sven Hannemann, Sven Stryker, Sławomir Wrzesień, T.S. Luikart, T.W.Wombat, Tablesaw, Tadeusz Cantwell, TAK, Tanya Cohan-Diaz, Tapani Tiilikainen, Tas Stacey, tavernbman, Ted Cabeen, Ted Novy, Ted Williams, teeter, Tellef, Thail, That One Die That Never Lets You Down, The Campbells, The Daughters of Verona, The Great and Mighty Neb, The guys at Fort Nerd, The High Lord Mhoram, of the Dark Ones, Master of the Black Citadel, Doctrina Magicus, The Infamous P.I.G., The Lord of Lime Sherbert, The Magus!!!11!!, the memory of Ada Lovelace, The Memory of Dave Arneson, The Nashv​ille Irreg​ulars, The Secret DM, The Sutra of Supreme Excellence, TheCatfish, Theron Teter, Thibault Mesmin d’Estienne, Thomas Foss Christensen, Thomas Ryan, Thomas Ulricht, Thorbjørn Steen, ThorDiantral, Thriondel Half-Elven, Tiago Marinho, Tim “Buzz” Isakson, Tim Ballew, Tim Hutchings, Tim Knight, Tim McCracken, Timothy Sanders, TJBailey, Todd Mitchell, Todd Roy, Todd Zircher, Tolly, Tom Cadorette, Tom Flanagan, Tom Idleman, Tom Ladegard, Tom Lumley, Tom McCarthy, Tom Reynolds, Tomasz Pudło, Tomek Filip, Tony, Tony, Tony Dijkstra, Tony Eng, Tony Indurante, Tony Love, Tony Reyes, Topi Makkonen, Torolf, Trachalio, Tracy Barnett/Sand &amp; Steam Productions, Tracy Hurley, Travis Bryant, Travis Scott, Trent Casey, Trent Yacuk, Trevis Martin, Trey Mercer, Trollhawke, Troy “Wrongtown” Hall, Troy Gilbert, Troy M. Costisick, Tuomas, Turk, txelu, Ty Sawyer, Tyler Jones, Tyler Lanser, Uffe Thorsen, Ulysses, Umberto Pignatelli, Unisprink, Vacuumjockey, Vera Vartanian, Vernon Lingley, Veronica Courage Wakefield, Victor Lane, Victor Maslov, Victor Wyatt, Victoria Uney, Viktor Haag, Ville Halonen, Vinicius Lessa, Vites, Vlad Del Cid, Vladimir Dzundza, Vladimir Filipović, W. Scott Jones, Wade “Belzain” Ussery, Walt Robillard, Warrbo, Warren “Mook” Wilson, Warren Merrifield, Wayne “Lumrunner” Humfleet, Wayne Arthurton, Wayne Lauer, Wei-Hua, Hsieh, Wes Price, Weston Clowney, White Paws, Whitt, Wilhelm Fitzpatrick, Will Ijebor, Will Robot, Will Thibault, Will Vesely, William “CallMeWilliam” Nichols, William Ansell, William Carroll, William Fischer, William Gerke, William K Wood, William Koch, Willis Scilacci, Wing Chan, WJO III, Wojciech Gębczyk, Wolfberry, WOoDY, Wothbora, wraith808, Wyatt Camp, Xander Veerhoff, Xavier Aubuchon-Mendoza, Xellos, cleric of coins, xiangh, Yan Prado, Yoki Erdtman, Yragael, Z. Dettwyler, Zach Clay, Zach Gourley, Zach Peters, Zachary Hall, Zachary Sylvain, Zachary Williams, Zack Kline, Zack Woodard, Zane Ewers, zero.executioner, Zippy Schindler, Zontco Gaming Division, ZSP, östen petersson</p>
</Story></Root>
